<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some thoughts concerning the life to come with a brief account of the state of religion as it is now in the world.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61224</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5138</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37589</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16976811</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16976811</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105603</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61224)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105603)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1159:42)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some thoughts concerning the life to come with a brief account of the state of religion as it is now in the world.</title>
                  <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Richard Stafford.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained and tightly bound with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Future life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105603:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105603:1"/>
            <p>SOME THOUGHTS CONCERNING <hi>The Life to Come:</hi> WITH A Brief Account Of the State of Religion, As it is now in the World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:105603:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105603:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>OF making many Books there is no end,</hi> ſaid the wiſe <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> in his time; which hath been ſince fulfilled in ſuch a degree, and to ſuch a meaſure, that through the multitude of <hi>Books,</hi> the intended Good and Benefit of them hath been loſt and defeated. For when the <hi>Great Truths of GOD</hi> have come forth and been publiſhed, People have not diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, diſcerned, and known them from the
<pb facs="tcp:105603:3"/> ordinary Imaginations and Sayings of other meer Humane Writers. But they have remained hidden, and <hi>not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood,</hi> Pſal. 106. 7. Acts 7. 25. by the Men of this World, and by the outward Worſhippers: Yea, they have not been <hi>Underſtood</hi> by many of the real Servants of GOD: They having not been ſo diligent (as in Duty they ought) to <hi>ſeek, Acts</hi> 15. 17. and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire out after all the Appearances and Manifeſtations of his <hi>Truth</hi> in the World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In every Nation</hi> (and ſo in every Sect or Party, however it is called or named) <hi>he that ſerveth GOD and worketh Righteouſneſs</hi> (which is a general and comprehenſive Speech, and doth include Obedience to all the Words of His Law) <hi>is accepted with Him,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:105603:3"/> 
               <hi>Acts</hi> 10. 34. To each Perſon which doth this, GOD affords the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Himſelf, and of the Things which pertain to his Kingdom. So that out of the Writings of the People of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Opinions and Perſuaſions among us (if that Foundation in them here mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed doth ſtand ſure) ſomewhat of GOD and of his Truth may be ſought after, and alſo had by the godly, honeſt, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Reader. But this is to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended unto, that as between the Miracles of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Inchantments of the Magicians, there is that manifeſt diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, That the one does not only much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the other; but the firſt do carry that Power, Evidence, and Demonſtration along with them, that the Magicians themſelves are forced to confeſs and acknowledge, <hi>This is the Finger of GOD,</hi> Exod. 8. 19. So likewiſe there is not only a manifeſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity
<pb facs="tcp:105603:4"/> between the Imaginations, Subtlety, and Sophiſtry of Satan (which have alſo an outward likeneſs unto, and imitation of Truth) and the <hi>certainty of the Words of Truth</hi> themſelves, or what <hi>Job</hi> calls <hi>right Words,</hi> Chap. 6. 25. But further, there is obſerved to be a continued Vein of Holineſs, and <hi>a Spirit of the Fear of the Lord,</hi> which runs throughout the Writings of ſome Men more than others. Here again theſe are exceeded by others alſo, who are yet mightier and greater than they in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, and in the diſpenſation of his Goſpel: For there is a real difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween what is meerly pious and devotional, or thoſe common things, which are univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally known, and obvious already; and the making known the <hi>Great Truths of God,</hi> or thoſe <hi>new Things which he doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, Before they ſpring forth, I tell you of them,</hi> Iſa. 42. 9. Which God doth tell an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:105603:4"/> declare unto Mankind, by ſome particular Saint or Servant of his.</p>
            <p>Now whether I my ſelf ſhall fall under the ſame Imputation which I here tacitly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend in other Writers; or whether I do here bring forth out of my Treaſury ſuch Things new and old; which in themſelves are indeed worthy to be made publick; or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet further, I do not expreſs out thoſe <hi>Truths of God</hi> (which as it is my Duty to write, ſpeak, and make known; ſo it is the Duty of the People of this my Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to read, hear, and <hi>receive into their knowledge,</hi> Rom. 1. 28.) I refer all this to the <hi>ſpiritual man who judgeth all things,</hi> 1 Cor. 1. 15. in this mean while, as it will be yet more clearly diſcerned and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by God and his Saints at the laſt Day.</p>
            <p>It hath been obſerved of <hi>John</hi> the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, that in his Goſpel he doth ſet down
<pb facs="tcp:105603:5"/> and mention what was omitted by the other three <hi>Evangeliſts;</hi> for whereas they all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat and confirm the ſame things, he doth record that as to which they are ſilent; ſo it hath been and ſhall be my conſtant Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod and Reſolution, only to publiſh thoſe uſeful Truths and <hi>weightier Matters of the Law,</hi> which have been hitherto <hi>omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> (ſee <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. 23.) in the Books and Sermons of other Writers and Preachers: And tho' I have already employ'd the <hi>Preſs</hi> proportionally for one of my Circumſtances, Condition, and Years; yet I ſhall never be ſo voluminous as <hi>Origen</hi> of old (who is reported to have made ſix thouſand Books) or as <hi>Toſtatus</hi> and <hi>Richard Baxter</hi> of later Times. But as I hope to be accepted of Him, who <hi>comes quickly, and his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is with him, to give to every man according as his Work ſhall be,</hi> Rev. 22. 12. I know that the Goodneſs and
<pb facs="tcp:105603:5"/> Worth thereof, doth lie not ſo much in its quantity, as its quality (as a little Diamond is of more value and eſtimation than a much greater common Stone) ſo <hi>I had rather ſpeak five,</hi> or a very few <hi>Words</hi> with knowledge and underſtanding, that by my Voice I might teach others alſo (which may be unto Men to edification, exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and comfort) than <hi>ten thouſand Words</hi> in uſeleſs Notions, or rather Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, in meer ſmooth Language, or in vain-jangling and matters of doubtful diſputation; the former of which do divert and turn aſide the Mind from the one thing needful; and the latter do rather mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter unto ſtrife than unto godly edifying.</p>
            <p>This ſmall enſuing Treatiſe is an eſſay and endeavour to the only good and right end of ſeeking the preſent Peace and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Welfare of men and women; I do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>write unto them of the common</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:105603:6"/> 
               <hi>Salvation.</hi> The Contents and ſubject Matter thereof may be apprehended from the Title-Page. Where the Failings, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, Infirmities, the Sins and <hi>Errours of the People</hi> are ſpoken of: This is for <hi>Doctrine,</hi> for <hi>Reproof,</hi> for <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,</hi> for <hi>Inſtruction in Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> And tho' perhaps there may not be altogether that exactneſs of Art, Method, and Connexion (whereof ſome <hi>Scribes</hi> have been more curious and careful, than of the Subſtance of the Things they have delivered) yet herein we have a great part of the <hi>Scripture</hi> for our enſample, which was given by <hi>Inſpiration of God,</hi> and is profitable for things which make us wiſe unto Salvation, that the Man of God may be perfect, thoroughly furniſhed unto all Good-works, albeit it is not like unto Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes framed by <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Man's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105603:6"/>
            <head>SOME THOUGHTS <hi>Concerning the Life to come,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold, now are we the Sons of God; and it doth not yet appear what we ſhall be; but we know that when he ſhall appear, we ſhall be like him; for we ſhall ſee him as he is,</hi> 1 John 3. 2.</p>
            <p>COncerning this thing of future and endleſs Life, I have great thought and ſearching of Heart: My Soul doth ſhrug within me, when in my Bed I think upon it throughly. Now I am as yet in this Life; but when that Moment ſhall come, in which I muſt be diſlodged from this Body, there ſucceeds Judgment and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and ſtrict requiring for all thoſe Omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Good and Duty which I have been guilty of; which are now utterly gone by,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105603:7"/> and cannot be retrieved for all eternity. Trial was once had, but now it is over, even as to all the Days and Doings of this Life here upon Earth. Now the Days are paſſing, and we are as yet in the Fleſh; but then they will be all over, and gone, and our Spirits will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from hence: Then ſhall they remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>(Luke</hi> 16. 25) the ſeveral Steps and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſages of our Life here on Earth, which at firſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may ſeem as faint as the remembrance of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Night-Viſion, or of the things which hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been lately, or long ſince paſt. But they ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be all call'd over again, and appear before us<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> All the Thoughts, Words, and Actions of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> paſt Life, will remain preſent before the Sou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and appear more lively, and make yet a grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter impreſſion (becauſe then ſhe is to receiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> accordingly) than when they were firſt done.</p>
            <p>The Word of Inſtruction which doth ariſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hence, is, that every thing now ſhould be ſo done as it will be then wiſhed and deſired that it ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been done; and this is to ſtrive to the utmoſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pleaſing and finding acceptance with Almigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty God. In what fear ſhould we paſs the tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of our ſojourning! How ſhould we improv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> every moment of our precious Time, and n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuffer the leaſt portion thereof to paſs away i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unprofitable and vain things! The diſpropo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion between Time and Eternity is vaſt, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as much greater as between the whole Ocea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:105603:7"/> and a ſingle Drop; or as the whole gathering <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Waters is to a narrow Gulph, or Stream. The Rivers run to the Sea, and in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er as ſoon as we draw Breath, we are gliding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n 'till we launch forth; and are ſwallowed up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto Eternity. The Odds will be as great, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ather more exceeding, than when one (who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as impriſoned in a dark Dungeon, or cub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed up in a narrow cloſe Room) is let out to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he liberty of the whole Earth: Or like a Swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow (which for a little time was pent up in a Cage) is let out again to fly up and down in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he wide and immenſe Regions of Air. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lteration and Change which will be then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ade upon us, is yet more unconceivable. It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth not yet appear what we ſhall be. Now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e know nothing or but little of the Soul; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſhall then perceive nothing beſides the Soul. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow we are wholly taken up with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erns of the Body, then we ſhall have nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o do with it. And ſo though our Bodies do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oulder towards the Duſt, and then ſeem to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tterly loſt; yet it is not ſo for ever, for they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>all be raiſed up again, and rendred glorious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd incorruptible. Now we do mind (if not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nly, yet chiefly) things ſenſible and carnal; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut then we ſhall be wholly taken up with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onſideration of things ſpiritual: The whole Creation, with all the Things and Works of God, will be more clearly manifeſted before
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105603:8"/> us, and underſtood by us, than they are now, as much as the Underſtanding of a Man doth exceed and ſurpaſs the Conception and Inſtinct of a Beaſt. It will be a very great change and renewal of things, now no more to turn to Corruption, nor to be deſtroyed, nor yet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved. But as it is ſaid of <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> That he <hi>abideth a Prieſt continually,</hi> Heb. 7. 3. By which Word <hi>Prieſt,</hi> according to its firſt inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, is ſignified the moſt Sanctified and Holy, and Choice of the People: <hi>And ye ſhall be unto me a Kingdom of Prieſts, and a holy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> Exod. 19. 6. from whence cometh that Word <hi>Clergy.</hi> So in like manner it may be affirmed, when thoſe true Things are erected and ſet up (whereof the Things heretofore made and now in being are but the figure) when the new Heavens and the new Earth are created which are ſpoken of in <hi>Iſai.</hi> 65. 17. then (if we may ſo ſpeak after the manner of Men, with much humility, trembling, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, that it may be underſtood by their Capacities) God hath done his beſt: <hi>For the new Heavens and the new Earth which I will make, ſhall remain</hi> (obſerve that) <hi>before me, ſaith the Lord,</hi> Iſai. 66. 22. This Word <hi>Remain,</hi> doth denote an eternal unchangeable ſtate, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is to laſt for a time, if it be a thouſand or million of Years, that is tranſitory; for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral parts and portions of Time do paſs away, and ſucceed one another.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:105603:8"/>
            <p> Now there is both Time and Motion, which are relative Terms; and theſe do point forth unto, as they will be ſwallowed up at length in the eternal Reſt: <hi>The whole Earth is at reſt and quiet; they break forth into ſinging,</hi> Iſai. 14. 7. This doth reſpect and look back unto that Confuſion, Deſolation, Deſtruction, Trouble, and Wearineſs which hath been heretofore on the Earth, when there was fear and weeping. It is before ſaid, <hi>The Lord ſhall give thee reſt from thy ſorrow, and from thy fear, and from thy hard bondage wherein thou waſt made to ſerve,</hi> verſ. 3. Theſe former evil things ſhall be done away, and the contrary good things ſhall ſucceed in the room thereof: And though this will in ſome meaſure be fulfilled in the latter days on the Earth, when the Sinners (who cauſe all this evil and trouble) ſhall <hi>be conſumed out of the Earth, and the wicked ſhall be no more,</hi> Pſal. 104. 35. For in what Prayer the Spirit of Truth doth dictate, is included a Promiſe that ſo it ſhall be. And then the People who inhabit here, ſhall practice the ſame Holineſs, and live in peace, as in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which is above, which is the Mother of us all. Which Word <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> by Interpretation is the <hi>Viſions of Peace.</hi> Though this will be in a leſs degree and more imperfect manner, juſt before the Church on Earth ſhall be received up, and ſwallowed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that of Heaven: And it ſhall then come to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105603:9"/> paſs, that the whole Creation ſhall be at reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and quiet: They ſhall ſing for joy, and brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> forth in loud Voices, and everlaſting Hallelu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>jahs, as is deſcribed in the Revelations: They ſhall not only be ſo as to reſt and inward peace of Soul and Spirit, but alſo as to outward Reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Motion: <hi>The Sun ſhall no more be thy ligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by day,</hi> thy Sun ſhall no more go down, <hi>neither ſhall thy Moon withdraw it ſelf; for the Lord ſhall be unto thee an everlaſting Light,</hi> Iſai. 60<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 18, 19. So ſhall it no more rejoyce as a ſtrong Man to run a Race, nor any longer continue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his going forth from the end of Heaven, nor his Circuit unto the ends of it; but the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the thing will then alſo ceaſe, and God Himſelf will then ſupply that immediately to his living Creatures and Spirits, which they had before by the means and inſtrumentality of the inanimate Creatures. There ſhall be no more any weary Beaſt; but if theſe ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and irrational Creatures, ſhould be raiſed up alſo to being and life again, anſwerable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, but yet much exceeding that ſtate they were in here, the Ox ſhall ſtill continue ſtrong to labour, yet all Labour; as to the wearineſs thereof, ſhall be done away, both with Men and Beaſts, <hi>when theſe times of refreſhing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord,</hi> Acts. 3. 19. The Holy Ghoſt hereby ſignifying, that they being then more nearly and immediately in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105603:9"/> the preſence of God (where <hi>is fulneſs of joy, and at whoſe right hand there are pleaſures for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more)</hi> all Refreſhing, Content, Satisfaction, yea, all Happineſs doth ariſe from Him, as Waters do flow from the Fountain, Light doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the Sun, or as Heat doth iſſue forth from burning fire, to the things that are next unto it.</p>
            <p>And therefore we ſhould not ſo much learn (for the general belief and apprehenſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is already ingraffed into the Minds of all Men) as practiſe this great Diverſity, That this Life and Earth is the place where we muſt meet with Labour and Wearineſs: But only in the ſucceeding State and Heaven, there is an utter exemption and perfect freedom from theſe and the like evil things. From hence we ſhould obſerve diligently, that when any thing in the Service of God, or in our Way to Heaven, ſeems harſh, uncouth, or aukward, and we are much againſt it; yet we ſhould thence in no wiſe refrain, neglect, or omit it; becauſe it is not only a Temptation to hinder and keep off from the beſt things, but alſo there is ſome irkſomneſs and labour in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry nature thereof, which we muſt reſolutely ſtrive againſt, and do it for all. There is the greateſt Oppoſition againſt, and Temptation annexed to the beſt Works, either to neglect or deſiſt, or be idle therein: <hi>For except we had</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:105603:10"/> 
               <hi>lingered, ſurely we had now returned this ſecond time,</hi> Gen. 43. 10. And ſo except we had loitered or been ſlothful, ſo much might have been done, as that ſuch a thing had been performed or finiſhed by this time, or long before. Now the beſt of Works is the bringing forth, and making known of divine Truths: For Satan hath the greateſt wrath, and ſheweth forth the moſt letting againſt this. He who now letteth, will let, until he be taken out of the way, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 17. For the Truth doth teach us how we may pleaſe God, and obtain his Favour: It doth point and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect us certainly in the ſeveral things of this Life, where and how to walk, that we may be all along in the way to Heaven, without going aſide to the right hand, or to the left. It is like a Pillar on a Road with written Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections on it, which tell us exactly the way from place to place, as alſo whither ſuch a By-road or turning aſide leads; or like a ſure Compaſs, by which thoſe who go down to the Sea in Ships, and occupy their Buſineſs in great Waters, do ſteer their courſe: Like the Sun by Day, or the Moon by Night, or as a Light ſhining in a dark place keeps our feet from ſtumbling; and by this we are enabled to go whither we intend and would be: So this Beam or Ray of heavenly Light doth conduct us through this dark Vale and perplex Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105603:10"/> of this World, unto the heavenly <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan: And thine Ears ſhall hear a word behind thee, ſaying, This is the way, walk ye in it, when ye turn</hi> aſide <hi>to the right hand, and when ye turn to the left,</hi> Iſai. 30. 21. Which Word ſpeaks to the Heart that it receives and conceives there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in clear and diſtinct Thoughts; which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain may be ſpoken forth, or written. So that as God directeth ſuch a Saint, or Servant, in all his Ways, he may be able to direct others which are in doubt and perplexity, by the ſame Word of Inſtruction wherewith them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are directed of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 4. And ſo by the ſame Word themſelves are perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, they may perſuade others.</p>
            <p>We ſhould retire inward, and get within, and give diligent attentive heed unto what God doth reveal and make known there; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther concerning his Law, which he would have us to obey, or concerning his Will, which he would have us to do; what are our beſt, true, ſubſtantial, and moſt ſignificative Thoughts, as they are abſtracted from Sin and Paſſion, and ſeparated from the Cloud of Ignorance. Now becauſe Thoughts are infinite, and Words many, therefore we are not to write down, and publiſh forth every one that doth ariſe and proceed forth from the Heart and Tongue, but only ſuch as are new <hi>(Iſai.</hi> 42. 9.) and true, more than is clearly known already, or through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105603:11"/> underſtood. And this ſhould be conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerved in writing of Books; for if all was printed which Thoughts could imagine, or Words diverſifie, I ſuppoſe that the whole World would not contain the Books which ſhould be written, and they would be all without Good or Benefit. It ſhould be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Rule when we write or publiſh concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning any ſubject, not to repeat and inſert a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain what hath been already ſaid. And ſo what new and uſeful Thoughts do ariſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this future and endleſs Life, the ſame are to be made known. But what doth make us to ſhrug and be afraid thereat, is the vaſt importance of the thing, it being a deciſion for everlaſting Happineſs or Miſery; and then becauſe we have not ſo lived as we ſhall wiſh that we had done; yea, and if it was ſo done, we ſhall again deſire with unexpreſſible anguiſh and earneſtneſs, that we had done better in the ſeveral Inſtances: For we ſhall then perceive our particular failings, wherein and how we came ſhort of what God required of us, and what we might have done. If we have ſinned and done evil, we ſhall wiſh that we had never come forth into being. O what ſelf-indignation and bitter reflection will there then be, if we were not imploy'd, whilſt in life, about what was proper for us to have done! And when things have in ſome meaſure been
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105603:11"/> done rightly, then alſo will be deſires that it had been better, and that we had been more diligent and abounding in the ſame. To appear before the Great God, and to fly out into the unknown parts of the World; to be launched forth into the vaſt Regions of Air; and if they are not entred into, yet to have a clearer and nearer proſpect of the higheſt Heavens; and then to find that change and diverſity upon it ſelf in all things, over what it was with her in the Body; All this ſeems fearful and aſtoniſhing. Though I had all Knowledge and all Faith, whereby I could remove Mountains which now intercept and hinder the ſight of Eternity, yet I could not deliver the thouſandth part thereof, that it may be conceived and apprehended as it ſhall be then known and experienced. Now the Soul is in Priſon, and holden under Fetters and Chains of Fleſh; but when the Angel of Death knocks them off, then ſhe breaks forth as Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out of a Cloud, and is altogether as quick in her motion. This we may know and be aſſured of, by the quickneſs of Thought, and by Sight, the principal Senſe and Operation thereof: For our Thoughts will run to and fro, from Eaſt to Weſt, from North to South, faſter than the Sparks among the Stubble, even in a moment of Time. For ſo our Eyes reach up unto Heaven at the firſt opening the Lid
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105603:12"/> thereof; ſo the Spirit of a Man will, in the twinkling of an eye, waft it ſelf throughout the whole Univerſe. Beſides the quickneſs of its motion, it is eminent for its tenuity, whereby it will paſs through the moſt firm Bodies. Now the Soul is wrapt up in a ſmall Body, and ſeems to be little more than nothing; but then it will be exceeding ſubtle and ſmall, and then it will be gathered up unto the Father of Spirits.</p>
            <p>As aforeſaid, People will then perceive and remember, that it would be infinitely better for them to have done exactly according to the Will of God, than to have acted at that confuſion and uncertainty with which the World goes on now after their own Ways, and in their own Wiſdom and Will. It is a frequent form of ſpeech in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> and in the other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, That when God doth bring his Judgment and Puniſhment on the Inhabitants of the Earth, then they ſhall know that the Lord hath not ſaid thus in vain. So when the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is to be given, and ſome are made up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Lord's Jewels, then ſhall they return and diſcern between the righteous and the wicked, <hi>between him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not,</hi> Mal. 3. 17, 18. So when this Generation of Men and Women is carried off from the Earth, as the former already are, and as we go off day by day in our ſeveral Perſons; then we ſhall return (that is, to the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105603:12"/> proper Underſtanding of Men) and diſcern that it would be better to have lived other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. The conſideration whereof will raiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation and wrath, tribulation and anguiſh in the Soul for having done evil, becauſe there comes of it puniſhment, and alſo loſs of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding and eternal Happineſs: To what is doubt now and dull apprehenſion, then will be the greateſt certainty and moſt lively ſenſe that ſo it would have been.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let the Heathen be awakened, and come up to the Valley of Jehoſhaphat,</hi> &amp;c. Joel 3. 12. By which phraſe of <hi>awakened,</hi> we learn that the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of God, and the Chriſtian ſpiritual Life, is as much beyond that of Heathens and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Men, as waking is to ſleep. And even in ſerving of God there are proportionable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, which do exceed the ſervice of God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the common ſtandard and ſize of the World, as real Action is beyond Dreaming. But then according to Truth, and as it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all. This Life, with all its activities, is as much leſs, and comes ſhort of the future Life, as ſleeping now is to waking, or as the abſolute death of the Body is to the breathing thereof in ſleep; or as fire it ſelf doth exceed the remote and diſtant heat thereof; or as the light of the Sun ſhining in its brightneſs, is much more than the dim light of a Candle. And ſo the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and employment, with all the other things
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105603:13"/> pertaining to it, do proportionably as much exceed the other. And ſo the Happineſs and Good which God hath prepared for his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and which he will inveſt them withal, doth yet ſeven times exceed the utmoſt appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion and thoughts any one hath concerning it. <hi>As we have heard, ſo have we ſeen,</hi> Pſal. 48. 8. (and yet much more abundantly) <hi>in the City of the Lord of Hoſts, in the City of our God; God will eſtabliſh it for ever. Selah.</hi> Whereby is denoted a contrariety and diverſity to the things here, which are but periſhing, and do paſs away: <hi>We have thought of thy loving kindneſs, O Lord, in the midſt of thy Temple,</hi> verſ. 9. Now this Temple is the World, and accordingly the <hi>Jews</hi> faſhioned their outward Temple made with hands, according to the ſimilitude there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and the Earth is obſerved to be placed in the exact midſt of the World. So that it is no forced conſtruction, but the very natural mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereof. That in this ſhort time we did live and inhabit here on this Earth, we thought of the loving kindneſs of God; not ſo much what we were ſenſible of then, but chiefly what he did intend to do further for his Creatures. It is elſewhere written, <hi>Men's Hearts failing them for fear, and for looking after thoſe things which are coming on the Earth,</hi> Luke 21. 16. So it will be with them who have been ungodly and wicked; but to the good and obedient, it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105603:13"/> is joyful Hope, and comfortable Expectation, either to look after what things are coming on the Earth, or what ſhall be ſhortly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted before them. Day unto Day uttereth Speech, and Night unto Night ſheweth Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. As every day bringeth forth ſomething that is remarkable of what is done here throughout the World: There is ſomewhat more, or new, if not in its ſelf, yet in its per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or in the manner and place of acting: So the Servant of God, who is endued with Faith and Knowledge, as every day he makes nearer approaches to the things unſeen, ſo he is in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of further knowledge and diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them: As the Traveller upon every five or ſix miles advance, hath a new and freſh Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon opened unto him; ſo in the ſucceſſion of Days, and Weeks, and Months, and Years, we know more ſpiritually concerning God, and alſo more clearly and diſtinctly concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the other Life. Sometimes we are upon the Mountains, and then in the Valleys; our Mind is now pure, lifted up, and dwelling in Heaven; again it is caſt down, and become altogether earthly and ſenſual. Sometimes we have clearneſs and brightneſs of light, then a cloudy day (ſee <hi>Zech.</hi> 14. 6.) now there is a glimmering of morning and evening, and then again we are fallen into the darkneſs of night. It is thus differently with us throughout the ſeveral times of our Life, as to our apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105603:14"/> of things ſpiritual and eternal. Sometimes we are clear, and then again cloudy: We are ſometimes in the twilight; yea, we become more dark, and at ſome times are in utter darkneſs concerning them. And this doth not ſo much depend upon ſet times and ſeaſons, but it happens thus diverſly with us as we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſin; which makes God forſake and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw his Communications from us. Again, when we walk before him in all ſobriety, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and duty, as is well-pleaſing in his ſight, then he doth afford the Communications and Manifeſtations of himſelf to us.</p>
            <p>Lord, how wilt thou manifeſt thy ſelf to us, and not to the World? But there is certainly a different and another Manifeſtation, whereby God appears and diſcovers himſelf to his elect Servants, than as he is apprehended by the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of the World. Tho' to them it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what hard to diſcern as much, and truſt in him, God doth commonly more ſhew and manifeſt himſelf in time of trouble, both to comfort and uphold the Spirits of his Creatures and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and alſo to make known unto them how they ſhall be delivered. This doth ſeem a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, ſtrange, and contrary kind of way, which the worldly Man may deſpiſe, and even the experienced Soul will hardly believe it at firſt; ſo hidden are the ways and dealings of God, even of his preſent Diſpenſations towards his Creatures. But the future things are much
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105603:14"/> more wrapt up in a myſtery, and within the veil. Were we as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> was in the Viſions of God, or did we, like <hi>Stephen, Paul,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> ſee the Heavens opened; <hi>And the Temple of God was opened in Heaven, and there was ſeen in his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the Ark of his Teſtament.</hi> Rev. 11. 19. or if the Skreen of theſe outward viſible things was withdrawn; ſo that with the eyes of our Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding being enlightned, we did clearly perceive the inward and ſpiritual, What are the moſt great and glorious Cities here on Earth, to that which is <hi>on the ſides of the North, the City of the great King,</hi> Pſal. 48. 2. What are the Kingdoms and Courts of this World, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of the greatneſs of God, and to the innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable company of Angels that are about his Throne, to the thouſand thouſands that mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to him, and to the ten thouſand times ten thouſand which ſtand before him! It is not ſo much as thoſe little Flies and Inſects, which move up and down, and make a ſmall hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and noiſe in the Air; for tho' now we are ſo pent up within, and taken up with our Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Creatures, that they are to us in a manner all in all: Yet did we with that God-like part in us (I mean our Souls) aſcend up above, and and get out from among them, and thence look down upon the Inhabitants of the Earth, as ſo many ſhort-liv'd Graſhoppers, then we ſhould conceive of, and know them as they are in their true nature: For the beſt way to know
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105603:15"/> any thing as it ought to be known (by which phraſe the Apoſtle doth difference it from that firſt general apprehenſion or ſuperficial out-ſide knowledge which the multitude take up with) is to get out and ſeparate from among our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and to be as abſtracted as ever we can from all ſenſible things.</p>
            <p>And then we ſhould wait ſome conſiderable time, before the great and precious Truths do come in. It was uſual with the Prophets, when they were conſulted upon any great difficulty, or when they were to give a Meſſage of their own accord to the People, to be in a ſtate of ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and retirement, with Prayer and Faſting for ſome conſiderable time before. We read that the Word of the Lord came to <hi>Ezekiel</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeven days, to <hi>Jeremiah</hi> after ten days. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, it is elſewhere ſaid, That <hi>it came unto him after many days.</hi> And ſo our ſelves have found, that when we have been upon the ſearching out, and contemplation of divine Truth, that the beſt and and moſt precious Truths, the new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt diſcoveries and ſuch things as we have never thought, heard, or read of before, they do moſt commonly come into our Mind, after two or three hours attendance upon Meditation, where hath been no manner of hinderance and interruption to the current of our Thoughts, by the intervening of other things, or reſorting to other Buſineſs. And therefore we ſhould do well herein to beware of one Device of Satan,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105603:15"/> That if no anſwer comes preſently from God, or if we do not run on cleverly in the things pertaining to his Kingdom, then he ſuggeſts to leave quite off, and not to wait on the Lord any longer. Sometimes we thus loſe the coming to the knowledge of ſuch and ſuch Truths concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Law and Judgments of God, which <hi>would be better unto us than thouſands of Gold and Silver,</hi> Pſal. 119. 72. <hi>More to be deſired are they than Gold, yea, than much fine Gold,</hi> Pſal. 19. 10. <hi>Receive my Inſtruction, and not Silver; and Knowledge rather than choice Gold; for Wiſdom is better than Rubies; and all the things that may be deſired, are not to be compared to it,</hi> Prov. 8. 10, 11. The Holy Ghoſt here making this compariſon and preference in theſe three ſeveral places, as he knows what is in Man, what he is inclinable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd prone unto; hereby he gives us to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, That People by ſeeking after, and by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng wholly taken up with the outward things of this Life, (which are all had by Money) do neglect the Knowledge of God, and the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of his Truth, which he doth here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acitly diſſuade them from.</p>
            <p>Again, where any man is gifted and fitted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or the Work of the Miniſtry, or for the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng out, and making known of the Truths of God unto the World, there all outward things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ertaining to Life, or even for the charge and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>abour of publiſhing this Truth, ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rought ready to his hand, that he ſhould not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105603:16"/> miſemploy the leaſt portion of his time from the other holy and more excellent Work, in ſeeking out, and looking after theſe leſſer things, This is ſignified by the original ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of Tithes, to reap where they did not ſow, nor beſtow the leaſt bodily labour; but the Tenth was ſet out for them ready, for their immediate uſe and receiving: And alſo by that ſaying of our Saviour Chriſt unto his Diſciples: <hi>Other Men laboured, and ye are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into their Labours,</hi> John 4. 38. This Doctrine (which we preach not for our ſelves, but as it is the Commandment and Will of God) is clearly delivered by that Prophet, who there ſaw and ſpeaks of the Goſpel-times, tho' he lived under the Law: <hi>And ſtrangers ſhall ſtand and feed your flocks, and the ſons of the alien ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be your plow men and vine-dreſſers; but ye ſhall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> called the prieſts of the Lord, men ſhall call you th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> miniſters of our God,</hi> Iſai. 61. 5. 6. Others ſhould provide them Meat and Raiment (contained in the Word <hi>Flocks,</hi> Bread ſignified by <hi>Plow men,</hi> and Drink expreſſed by <hi>Vine-dreſſers)</hi> in which all the food and nouriſhment of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Life principally conſiſts: Which others are to get ready for them, whilſt they do only offe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> up Prayers unto God (for the Prieſts of ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> time did offer Sacrifice) and are wholly em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ploy'd in the miniſtration of his Word an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Truth. <hi>It is not reaſon that we ſhould leave th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Word of God, and ſerve Tables,</hi> Acts 6. 2. It is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:105603:16"/> reaſon that we ſhould neglect what is alike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to come unto eternal Life, to ſerve the mean neceſſities of this, tho' the hardſhip of the World doth force us to miſemploy much of our precious time this way.</p>
            <p>I have been often troubled and concerned that I ſhould be ſo cumbred about many things, and perhaps about ſome things which were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the proper End and Work I was ſent into this World for to do; or I being ſomewhat called thereto, yet I have intended too much that point only, or I have miſ-ſpent too much time therein; ſo that I ſhould go out of this Life before I had throughly thought of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and before I had finiſh'd what I came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this World for to do. How many precious Truths of more latitude, of greater concern, and of more univerſal uſe to all Men and Women in the general (which might be of inſtruction and edification for longer time, and even for the Generations to come; which do alſo more immediately reſpect the Church of God, and his elect Servants) might have been brought forth and publiſhed, inſtead of a leſſer matter of a National Revolution, which was done by a few thereof. And tho' their eternal Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was concerned herein (that being to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd no other way than by keeping the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God; yet it was not altogether ſo much relating to the great and common multitude, whoſe Souls are as highly eſteem'd
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105603:17"/> of God, as the Souls of the rich and mighty People. And then for my laying of divine Truths before them, they laid perſecution up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Loins, which cauſed diſturbance of Mind, and loſs of our precious Time. Hereby I came to loſe that lovely Awe and Dread, and that ſweet Sence of God, which did formerly dwell and abide upon my Soul and Spirit. O that I were as in the days of my youth, when the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret of God was upon my Tabernacle! Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by alſo I became inſenſible and unbelieving, as to the inviſible and future things of God, which heretofore my Heart was always full with the expectation of. I who have heard Words of God, and knew the Knowledge of the Moſt High, who was always looking after what I ſhall not ſee now, and ſtill beholding after what did draw nearer and nearer; yet again there did as it were Scales come over the Eyes of my Underſtanding, and I became as other ignorant ungodly People. In the multitude, hurry, and confinement of the City, I have not had thoſe pure enlightnings and clear communications of God, as I have had in mine own native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and under my Father's Roof; and I have ſeveral times deſired that I might recover and return to that ſtate again, and not ſpend my life upon one thing only, which is little more than a continued bringing forth unto trouble. But as I do day by day approach nearer and nearer unto this future Life and Immortality; ſo whether I
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105603:17"/> ſleep or wake, am buſie or idle, my Thoughts may be always thereupon, and be more lively concerning it, and I may be ſtill reaching forth after it. <hi>Looking for, and haſting unto the coming of the day of God,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 12. Whether we do think thereof, or not, we do continually run, yea, and fly towards it. But hereby the Holy Ghoſt doth teach and inſtruct us, That tho' we do move ſo faſt towards it, yet we ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it in our Thoughts, ſo we ſhould think more continually and earneſtly, as we come nearer in time, and ſee the day approaching. And this ſhould not be a vain ſpeculation, nor a meer thought only; but we ſhould ſtill be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the inquiry and examination, <hi>What we muſt do to be ſaved?</hi> And that we give all diligence to <hi>make our calling and election ſure,</hi> that ſo an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance may be miniſtred unto us abundantly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the everlaſting Kingdom of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Jeſus Chriſt; ſtill making Heaven ſure unto our ſelves, and endeavouring to make it yet more ſure.</p>
            <p>The Life which I now live, is by faith in the Son of God; and ſo when God and Chriſt do act altogether in us, and our whole Buſineſs is to pleaſe and approve our ſelves unto them, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and our future being is all in all of our Concern, and all our Works and Doings are brought in ſubordination under that; then we are Servants of God, and Chriſtians indeed. Tho' I have known ſuch after the fleſh, yet
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105603:18"/> henceforth I know them no more; nor yet will I walk after the manner of the fleſh, nor after the manner of the world, nor yet after the way of childhood, youth, vanity, or jeſting. We ſhould renounce the things that ſavour of men, nor make mention of them within our Lips. The Holy Ghoſt ſaith, by the mouth of <hi>Micah, Ariſe ye, and depart; for this is not your reſt, becauſe it is polluted,</hi> chap. 2. 10. This expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is in alluſion to Shepherds, who after they have fed one place well and throughly with their Flocks, and their feet have trodden, ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, or made the Paſtures to ſmell, then they remove to a freſh place and ground: So after we have throughly done the Buſineſs of Life in ſuch a thing, we ſhould not ſtill ſtick in that, but preſs further to the higher and greater Concern. <hi>The ſhepherds with their flocks ſhall come unto her; they ſhall pitch their tents againſt her, round about, they ſhall feed every one in his place,</hi> Jer. 6. 3. And when they have ſo done for ſome time, they take up, and remove to another. It is ſaid in the following Verſe, <hi>Wo unto us, for the day goeth away, for the ſhadows of the evening are ſtretched out.</hi> If we have not done our task, nor the work appointed for us whilſt we were here on this Earth, our Maſter in Heaven will call us to an account. <hi>Doth the plowman plow all day to ſow,</hi> Iſai. 28. 24. This would be too laborious and tireſome; for when tbe day is far ſpent, as towards two or three of the clock, he looks up
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105603:18"/> to the Winter-Sun, and concludes it is time to draw off. Our God hereby doth inſtruct us to diſcretion; and teach us, that when a great deal of our life is ſpent, and the day of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality is at hand, then let us make the three a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-cited Inferences, <hi>Ariſe and depart, for this is not your reſt.</hi> Which in the language of the Goſpel, that brings Immortality to light, ſpeaks on this wiſe: <hi>The Bridegroom is at hand, go forth to meet him.</hi> Tho' future life and immortality is coming faſt enough upon us, yet we ſhould run out before to prevent, meet, and anticipate it. I want Words to expreſs it according to the very meaning, purport, and requiring of the thing. As the Soul is juſt breaking forth out of this Shell of the Body, into endleſs life, the Babe ſhould leap in the Womb, and move it ſelf before, yea, and lift and aſcend its ſelf up, deſiring to be there. And as the Plowman draws off at ſuch a time of day, ſo we ſhould draw off our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, not only from the ſin and evil (for we ſhould be perfectly liſtleſs and dead as to them) but our deſires ſhould be drawn off utterly even from the lawful, neceſſary, and indifferent things of this World; We ſhould be as if we uſed them not, temperate in all things, and get above them.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of the different actings of Men, is according to the diverſity of the knowledge that is in them; as our Saviour anſwer'd him, who asked a good thing, and was doubtful
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105603:19"/> whether he ſhould receive it or not, <hi>According to thy Faith, ſo be it unto the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> So as to many fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture things we are doubtful, in the dark, or blind as towards them; yet as to the attainment of them, all Men act according as their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is: But with ſome it is imagination or fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood, when others do apprehend the thing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly as it is, and according to truth. Each M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n doth according to ſuch a number of thoughts within himſelf. Here again the Rule with ſome is to do according as the moſt do, and to walk according to the courſe of this World; to be guided by the Sayings and Opinions of the People, and by what ariſes to himſelf in his next and uppermoſt thought. Others do make the Word of God their ſet and conſtant Rule, and alſo they are led by the ſilent and inward Dictates of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>Now indeed all the days of a Man's life here on Earth do paſs away like a ſhadow; and ſo it is as to the good or evil, the conveniency or inconveniency, the comfort or irkſomneſs of them; both is but little, and it ſoon paſſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: But then at laſt comes the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, and diſtribution is made to every one of reward or puniſhment, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the deeds done in the Body, whether good or evil, true or falſe: And therefore it is mightily incumbent upon us to ſee well to it, becauſe that every word and action doth come into reckoning: For according to the deeds
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105603:19"/> done in the Body, ſo will God recompence, and ſo ſhall we receive; and therefore it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoves us to know and conſider before, in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we take in hand, or whatever our hand finds us to do, how this will paſs in the future examination and trial, and whether it will tend to our benefit or loſs at that day: Whatever thy hand finds thee to do; remember the end, and thou wilt never do amiſs; keep the Judgment of God always in thine eye, and thou wilt never go much aſtray. And ſo it comes to paſs, that where ſome do good, and others do evil; ſome behave themſelves rightly in ſuch a matter, and others behave themſelves wrong. It happens thus according to the different meaſure of knowledge which they have. Moreover, that the Heart be without knowledge it is not good. This knowledge is branched forth into the things that have been, the things that are, and the things that ſhall be; how God dealt with his People and Creatures which were before we were born, and who are gone off from the Earth before us; how it is between God and them, who are for a little while breathing here. But more eſpecially the earneſt expectation of the Creature ſhould be forward, after thoſe great and good things he will do, after this Earth is diſſolv'd, and after the new, eternal, and irreverſible ſtate of things is brought in. When he that for about 6000 years has been a turning Man to deſtruction, doth ſay again,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105603:20"/> 
               <hi>Return ye Children of Men,</hi> Pſal. 90. 3. The firſt is ſaid in the ſingle number, becauſe now they die ſeverally in their individual Perſons one after another. But the reſurrection will be in the plural, for they will be all rais'd, and brought up together at once. This will be a change and alteration to a witneſs (as we uſe this Phraſe in common proverbial ſpeaking) when mortality ſhall be ſwallow'd up of life, when this corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption ſhall put on incorruption, never more to ſee or turn again unto corruption. This natural Body ſhall be raiſed up a ſpiritual Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; We have not now thoughts to conceive, nor words to expreſs how or after what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the whole alteration will be; it makes us fear and ſhrug at the lively and through appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion thereof. Now we know what we are, but what we ſhall be after theſe Bones are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into dry Bones, and after they ſhall live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, O Lord, thou knoweſt; and alſo how it will be with us, when we ſhall be caught up into the Air, there ever for to remain with the <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now becauſe we hope, deſire, and would have the beſt things, whereof both the good and evil are in the hands and diſpoſal of God; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our way is to pleaſe him, and to get his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. The things which we do in order to God, that is call'd <hi>Religion,</hi> and it is either worſhip or obedience. Theſe two ſubjects, <hi>viz. Some Thoughts of the Life to come, and of the State of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion as it is now in the World,</hi> are fitly join'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105603:20"/> becauſe one of them is in order to the other: For the end of every Man's Religion (if he doth underſtand and practiſe it aright) is that he may pleaſe God, and that himſelf may be ſaved. Seeing that it is made known unto him, (both from his own Soul, and from the Book of the Lord, and alſo from what he hears by the hearing of the Ear) and he believes the ſame that he muſt live for ever, he cannot do otherwiſe than deſire to be happy for ever.</p>
            <p>This puts Mankind upon their ſeveral ways of pleaſing and finding acceptance with Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God; and they go on according to their own ſeveral Opinions, Perſuaſions, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations. What they do herein, is the hearing of Words, or the offering up of Prayers unto God. It is the Opinion of the Papiſts, that the Work done, and the bare outward uſe of the Ordinances, doth conferr Grace, and is accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able unto God: Others again of the Reformed Religion, do believe that this doth depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon the right intention and good heart of the Worſhipper; which is ſo in very truth, and according to the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the holy Scriptures. But ſtill there is a tincture and relick of this kind of Popery remaining at this day among the Proteſtants; for they think that they have done a great deal in order to God, by having kept his Ordinances, and becauſe they were continually before him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 7. and they did not omit them at any time. Indeed it was
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105603:21"/> well done herein, and one act of continued du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and obedience unto God; for as on the other ſide it is a ſign of open ungodlineſs and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, when they refuſe to tread God's Courts, ſo here it is a token of profeſs'd and viſible ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection unto God, when they do diligently and conſtantly keep his Ordinances, and never o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them at any time.</p>
            <p>My ſelf have reaſon to pray earneſtly unto God, that he will not reprove me becauſe my Sacrifices and Burnt-Offerings have not been continually before him; I have been forced to neglect his Publick Worſhip for many Lord's Days ſucceſſively, leſt the Sons of Violence, my Perſecutors, who are many in number, ſhould hale me again unto Priſon. And ſo becauſe I have not the benefit of them my ſelf, ſhall I go about in any wiſe to depretiate or leſſen from that juſt value and real goodneſs which ariſes from them? God forbid. There hath been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that tincture of Man's infirmity, who have calculated Religion according to their own circumſtances and condition, as to ſpeak ſome what more favourably of the omiſſion of that duty, which themſelves did not altogether ſo much practice, as again more excuſably of tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſin which themſelves were addicted and given unto. Thus far hath Partiality blinded them who herein have took part with their own Errours and Corruption. But amidſt all thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> weakneſs and fault of Man, the Word of God
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105603:21"/> is very pure; which doth not vary from her origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal purity, by any thing that Men would do, or by what they would faſten upon it from their own imaginations. To hide our ſin as <hi>Adam,</hi> or to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie or extenuate it, doth make it yet worſe and more provoking in the ſight of God; for it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to lay our hands upon our mouth, and to hold our peace, and to ſubmit unto the mercy and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right <hi>dealing of the Lord.</hi> Let my tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth, if I prefer ſecret commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God, before the worſhip of him in the Congregations of his People; or (as the manner of ſome is) to relinquiſh them wholly in order to enjoy, as they ſay, more private and inward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with their God, for his publick Worſhip on his own holy Day, doth take up but three or four hours of the Week, and the reſidue of their time they might allot for that. When both may ſtand conſiſtent, and be uſed ſucceſſively one with another, there is no need for one to joſtle or thruſt out the other: And let my hand like <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s wither, if I ſhould go about to lay hold on, or hinder the true Goſpel-Prieſthood in the miniſtration of their Office in the Temple: For it muſt be in ſome place, and it is better in ſuch a place which is ſet a-part wholly for this, and for no other uſe: And let my tongue never hold a Pen more, if I ſhould in the leaſt perſuade or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate unto People to neglect the aſſembling of themſelves together. My caſe is now ſomewhat like that of <hi>David,</hi> when he was <hi>hunted up and down</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:105603:22"/> 
               <hi>like a Partridge in the mountains. As the hart panteth after the water-brooks, ſo panteth my ſoul after thee, O God. My ſoul thirſteth for God, for the living God; when ſhall I come to appear before God! My tears have been my meat day and night, while they ſay continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unto me, Where is thy God? When I remember theſe things, I pour out my ſoul in me; for I had gone with the multitude; I went with them to the houſe of God, with the voice of joy and praiſe, with the multitude that kept holy-day,</hi> Pſal. 42. 1, 2, 3, 4. Then he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred and call'd to mind what refreſhings himſelf formerly had in the Aſſemblies; and there it was that he met with God; as God himſelf doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it elſewhere, appointing the manner of his Worſhip, he ſaith to this purpoſe: <hi>And there I will meet with thee, and commune with thee,</hi> Exod. 25. 22. In like manner my Soul doth pant and thirſt earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that I being once ſaved and delivered from mine Enemies, and from the hands of all that hate me, might ſerve him without fear, <hi>in righteouſneſs and holineſs before him all the days of my life,</hi> Luk. 1. 74. For this do I deſire to live, that I may amongſt his People worſhip God, according to the mind of the Spirit, that I may turn to the People of a pure language, and we may all ſerve the Lord with one Conſent. And tho' there is left in the midſt of us at this day an afflicted and poor People, yet they have not that full meaſure and higher degrees of knowledge and underſtanding, which were to be wiſh'd for, and deſired; nor yet do they truſt in the name of the Lord, as his People, or as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:105603:22"/> did of old time. Where are the People now upon Earth, who are as diligent and zealous in all the parts and ſeaſons of the Service of God; who do abound in good Works, and are bold, not fearing the face of Man, as they were in former days: Or ſuch as thoſe we read of in the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> or in the three firſt Centuries imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after thoſe days. <hi>Look down from Heaven, and behold from the habitation of thy Holineſs and of thy Glory: Where is thy zeal and thy ſtrength, and the ſounding of thy bowels, and thy mercies towards us? are they reſtrained?</hi> Iſa. 63. 15. The Prophet here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſeems to import as if God had turned his face another way, and doth not now behold the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Earth; and thereupon he prays un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, to <hi>look down again upon them,</hi> and as if God doth now with-hold his Communications, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd imparting of Good unto his Creatures: For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat which is of God in any of us, it is (if I may ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xpreſs it) but the conveying of ſo many Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icles of the Divine Nature into us: <hi>Every good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ift, and every perfect gift cometh down from above:</hi> Upon the right improvement and good uſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe Seeds and Principles of Goodneſs, God gives <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s more. But by that kind of ſpeech of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ention'd, and by what <hi>Ezekiel</hi> reciteth as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ying of others, <hi>The Lord hath forſaken the Earth.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd even his Spirit doth ſpeak to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe by the mouth of <hi>Jeremiah: Be inſtructed, O <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eruſalem, leſt my Soul depart from thee,</hi> Jer. 6. 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom all which we gather, that when the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105603:23"/> of the Earth are corrupt, or when they are univerſally given to ſuch a ſin (whatever it be, as it is now one, and then another, according as the courſe and faſhion of this World doth turn and lead unto) or to ſuch a thing which is beſides, or otherwiſe than the Law of God is. When <hi>they know not, nor will they underſtand, they walk on in darkneſs; all the foundations of the Earth are out of courſe,</hi> Pſal. 82. 5. Like as it was ſoon after the Creation: <hi>And God ſaw that the wickedneſs of man was great on the earth, and that every imagination of the thoughts of his heart was only evil continually: And it repented the Lord that he had made man upon the Earth, and it grieved him at his heart. And God looked upon the Earth, and behold it was corrupt; for all fleſh had corrupted his way upon the Earth,</hi> Gen. 6. 5, 6. So it is at this day. When he ſees them in ſuch a ſtate, he leaves them to themſelves; they will not come out of it, nor learn and receive more knowledge. And ſo it comes to paſs that God doth not dwell amongſt them: <hi>For ye are not my people, and I will not be your God,</hi> Hoſ. 1. 9.</p>
            <p>He is not ſlack or backward, as ſome Men coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſlackneſs or backwardneſs, in giving his gifts, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conveying his goodneſs unto Men; but they ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not qualified for the receiving thereof. Be ye clean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ye that bear the Veſſels of the Lord; for therefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it is that he doth not pour in of his holy Spirit, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe the Man or Woman is not cleanſed from all filthineſs of Fleſh and Spirit, and from all un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>righteouſneſs. God is before-hand with ever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:105603:23"/> Man; he gives to each a ſtock or talent, and to him that hath, ſhall be given; and from him that hath not, ſhall be taken away even what he ſeemeth to have; that is, he ſhall have yet leſs; for there muſt be ſomewhat, or elſe that could not be taken away; and then that is taken away from him that hath not; that is to ſay, that little which before he had. There is ſome little left remaining to prove and try him ſtill, whether he will abuſe or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove that very little. The truth of all this is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by experience; for there is none ſo very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly and wicked, but there are in them ſome ſmall ſparks or ſeeds of Goodneſs, ſome principles of Righteouſneſs and Truth do remain in them. Tho' with many all this is in a very imperfect man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, yet they have alſo ſome general Principles of God, and of the things pertaining to his Kingdom, and of future life and immortality. By this little God doth prove them whether they will keep his Commandments, or not; and whether they will underſtand and ſeek after God <hi>(Pſal.</hi> 14. 2.) and follow on to know the Lord. By that tincture and conception, and ſmall knowledge they have of him already, if they did once begin to do either, then he would give them more grace and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. So it is with the indifferent middle-ſize of People, yea, and with the beſt ſort of Chriſtians at this day. God is before-hand with all of them; for even they do not live up, nor act according to all and the utmoſt which God makes known un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and requires of them, and alſo gives them ſtrength to perform. It is agreeable with the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105603:24"/> and wiſdom of God, to do nothing which is ſuperfluous, or more than needs muſt; nor yet is he wanting in what means are abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary: <hi>I will cry unto God the moſt High, unto God that performeth all things for me,</hi> Pſal. 57. 2. Which he doth by little and little, and by unexpected ways. He ſees where his own People (for there is a fault and defect in them, even in them) do not obey thoſe ſecret motions of the Spirit which he doth already inſtill into them, and there he ceaſes to infuſe further motions, becauſe the former were quenched, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 19. deſpiſed or diſobeyed; and ſo they are forgotten by the perſon who had them; as alſo God hath withdrawn them: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if they were cheriſhed, and obeyed, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied withal, God would give them much more abundantly, and they would have it in full mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and running over.</p>
            <p>By doing the ſeveral acts of good and duty, we are more enabled and ſtrengthned to do ſo ſtill, and yet better and more abundantly in the kind. So by performing acts of Zeal, we grow more zealous; for theſe things are kept up by the uſe and exerciſe; as contrariwiſe upon the omiſſion &amp; neglect, they do languiſh and utterly wither away. Agreeable hereunto the Spirit ſpeaketh, <hi>Be watchful, and ſtrengthen the things which remain, that are ready to die,</hi> Rev. 3. 2. Thus it is, as to the ſeveral Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Gifts of the Spirit; and as to the good Works which are wrought in us, they are all to be acted and employed on their ſeveral objects, and as every opportunity is to be had; for by only
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:105603:24"/> keeping them within, and folding up theſe Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents in a Napkin, they ſerve as nothing; they grow liſtleſs, and ſubject to decay and periſh. As they ſaid in <hi>Acts</hi> 19. 2. <hi>We have not ſo much as heard whether there be any Holy Ghoſt;</hi> ſo it is with many Men and Women at this day: They do not ſo much as know and perceive whether there be any ſuch thing as motions and workings of the Holy Spirit, albeit God hath ſhewed it unto them, by having put ſome meaſure of the Spirit in them.</p>
            <p>For there is a reſidue of the Spirit, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2. 15. and a meaſure of the Spirit, <hi>John</hi> 3. 34. and there is a taking off of ſome of the Spirit, and a giving or dividing of it unto others, <hi>Numb.</hi> 11. 25. For <hi>all theſe worketh that one and the ſelf-ſame Spirit, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding to every Man ſeverally as he will,</hi> 1 Cor. 12. 11. Thus it is, that where God doth put his Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in Man and Woman, <hi>there is none that ſtirreth up himſelf to take hold of thee,</hi> Iſai. 64. 7. They do not ſtir up and actuate the Spirit that is in them. What Advice <hi>Paul</hi> gives unto <hi>Timothy, Neglect not the Gift that is in thee,</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 14. <hi>Wherefore I put thee in remembrance, that thou ſtir up the Gift of God which is in thee, by the putting on of my hands,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 6. is proper and neceſſary to every Chriſtian Soul; that they do not neglect any, but ſtir up all the <hi>Gifts</hi> and <hi>Graces</hi> which are in them: For want of which (as it is a general failure amongſt all Profeſſions and ſorts, however they are diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed or named) it comes to paſs that there are no ſuch Chriſtians now among us, as was in the days of the Apoſtles, and in the primitive Times.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:105603:25"/>
            <p> Where is now that fervent burning <hi>zeal</hi> for God and Chriſt, and for all the Commandments with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, or preferring of one thing before another? Where is that <hi>diligence</hi> and <hi>conſtancy</hi> in his Worſhip? Where is that lively Faith in God, with that willing ſubjection of themſelves to the Croſs, Perſecution, Suffering, and Trouble for the Word and Truth's ſake? Where are thoſe now-a-days that are not afraid of the face of Men, and of the blaſt of the terrible ones, which with them of old Time was as <hi>a ſtorm againſt the Wall,</hi> Iſai. 25. 4. making no impreſſion, much leſs cauſing them to yield; for they did remain unſhaken, and ſtood their ground ſtill. Or who is there now that doth not regard the Perſons of Men? Or if they do refrain from giving flattering Titles, yet do they not ſecretly accept Perſons? By which Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb Secretly, the Holy Ghoſt doth find them out. Who doth now come up to that unfeigned Love of the Brethren, ſo as <hi>to love one another with a pure heart fervently?</hi> Where is now that ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Bowels, and that moſt earneſt ſenſible Compaſſion one to another which we read they then had? Where is that laying down their Lives for the Brethren, and the following them to Priſons and to Death? They did formerly miniſter relief unto their Fellow-Chriſtians, tho' they were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden ſo to do by their Perſecutors. Where is now to be ſeen that ſelling of Lands and Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, to <hi>diſtribute to every Man according as he has need,</hi> as was in <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 34, 35. What is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:105603:25"/> of that plentiful Alms-giving, and abundant liberality, which was ſhewed forth in thoſe firſt and pureſt <hi>Ages?</hi> Is not that plainneſs and ſimplicity, and godly ſincerity (which was then in the hearts and practices of all the faithful) almoſt now gone off from the Earth; but only here and there ſome imperfect footſteps thereof are to be ſeen in a very few? Is that good Zeal of the ancient <hi>Jews</hi> now any where to be found, who would hazard and loſe their Lives, rather than they would ſuffer Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues to be ſet up before the Gates of the Temple, or eat Swines fleſh? And the like Zeal ſhould be indefinitely ſhewed forth for all the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, and for all the poſitive Duties of the Goſpel, without confining or limiting of it to one thing more than another. But now if any thing is done againſt any of the Commandments of the Lord, concerning things which ſhould not be done (ſee <hi>Levit.</hi> 4. 22, 27.) there is an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency and unconcernedneſs. Some could wiſh (but it will never be done with wiſhing) that things were right, and according to the Law of God, <hi>Ezra</hi> 10. 3. there is the utmoſt pitch of their Zeal. Tho' God hath given them knowledge and ability for doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for inſtruction in righteouſneſs, they would have God excuſe them now, and pardon them hereafter, if they neglect this gift in them. If preſent intereſt, or any doctrine or opinion, which is eſpouſed and peculiar; it perhaps giving denomination to ſuch a Sect or Party, is any wiſe concerned, here they
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:105603:26"/> will exert their Zeal, Knowledge, and Induſtry: But they will not in like manner contend earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the weightier matters of the Law, as <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Mercy, Faith,</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> to all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God; every one of which is to be obſerved towards, and by every Creature, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception or reſpect of Perſons.</p>
            <p>They ſay, Theſe things are ſufficiently known already: But are they practiſed and done accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly? Herein they ſpeak after a like unworthy manner, as thoſe who ſaid, <hi>Will a Man plead for</hi> Baal? <hi>let</hi> Baal <hi>plead for himſelf;</hi> and it is almoſt the ſame what they ſpeak in reference to the God of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> For if they may not ſo properly be ſtyled <hi>Scoffers of theſe laſt and worſt days;</hi> yet they are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, ſlothful, walking after their own Luſts, and ſaying, <hi>What need one do any thing for God? he will do his work for himſelf.</hi> This they are willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ignorant of, that there is ſuch a Duty, <hi>That peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould help the Lord againſt the mighty,</hi> Judg. 5. 23. which ſignifies the Sons of Violence and Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, who will do things of their own ſtrength, <hi>becauſe it is in the power of their hand,</hi> Mic. 2. 1. and they are not, nor yet will they be kept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the bounds of God's Commandments. But theſe People <hi>do err,</hi> (which they utter forth <hi>againſt the Lord,</hi> Iſai. 32. 5.) <hi>not knowing the Scriptures, nor the Power of God;</hi> nor yet the way of the preſent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of <hi>his Kingdom:</hi> For tho' the help which God doth upon Earth he doth it himſelf, yet it is always done by the Means and Inſtruments of his
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:105603:26"/> Servants, as they do act and exert forth thoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of <hi>Goodneſs</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> which he hath implan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in them. As the Apoſtle argues from this Word, <hi>Yet once more,</hi> Heb. 12. 27. ſo every Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, yea, the leaſt Word and Particle in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is obſervable. Where we read of ſome People that their <hi>Spirits were ſtirred,</hi> there is a motion or making known, or a Command of God to the Heart; which yet the Creature doth not obey. But where it is written God <hi>ſtirred up the Spirit of</hi> ſuch an one (as <hi>Gideon, David, Nehemiah, Zeruba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel)</hi> there the Perſon doth actually obey, and goes forth, and is doing according to the Work God calls and employs him about.</p>
            <p>Be inſtructed, all ye ſlothful and faint-hearted Chriſtians: God hath put nothing in vain in any Man or Woman. That <hi>Goodneſs</hi> which he firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graſſed, and doth afterwards infuſe, ſhould increaſe and grow up, and it ought to appear forth through the Perſon in whom it is. Agreeable hereunto is what our Lord ſaith and commands: <hi>Ye are the Light of the World; a City that is ſet on an hill cannot be hid; neither do Men light a Candle, and put it under a buſhel, but on a candleſtick, and it giveth light unto all that are in the houſe. Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good works, and glorifie your Father which is in Heaven,</hi> Matth. 5. 14, 15, 16. That which is of God in any Perſon, is either <hi>Goodneſs</hi> or <hi>Truth;</hi> and as <hi>Goodneſs</hi> ought to appear forth, ſo the <hi>Truth</hi> in him ought to be ſpoken out. For tho' the common Saying of the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:105603:27"/> World is (agreeable to the Wiſdom of the Fleſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is for ſloth, eaſe, and preſent ſafety) Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>all Truth is not to be ſpoken;</hi> yet we have learned a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nother way to Heaven. <hi>Lord, who ſhall abide in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tabernacle? Who ſhall reſt in thy holy Hill? He tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> walketh uprightly, and worketh righteouſneſs, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſpeaketh the truth in his heart,</hi> Pſal. 15. 1, 2. So tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as ſure as the Spirit of God doth here teach th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way to Heaven, and lay down the foregoing Qualifications and Conditions, which we muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have and do before we come there, whateve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Truth is in our heart (provided it be the Truth o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>God,</hi> as coming from <hi>Him,</hi> and ariſing out of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Word)</hi> we muſt and ought to ſpeak it, come what<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ever will hereof, if we do not mean to be diſap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pointed of Heaven at laſt. And if this doing ſhould bring trouble upon our Loins (for this Ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>jection the worldly-wiſe Man hath againſt thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Duty, and therefore he will refrain to utter it) w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> muſt do it for all that; this being that kind of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifold Tribulation which we muſt go through<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> before we enter into the <hi>Kingdom of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All People will not be ſaved who conſtantly go to <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Meeting;</hi> for of the four ſorts of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of the Word,</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. there is but one who beareth and bringeth forth <hi>fruit unto everlaſting life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> But there is another ſort which comes exactly to the preſent caſe: <hi>But he that receiveth ſeed into ſtony places, the ſame is he that heareth the word, and ano<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with joy receiveth it; yet hath he not root within him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelf, but dureth for a while; for when tribulation or</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:105603:27"/> 
               <hi>perſecution ariſeth becauſe of the word, by and by he is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffended,</hi> Mat. 13. 20, 21. There is no Perſon but who would willingly be ſaved, and doth perceive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome lightſomneſs and ſatisfaction to ariſe from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Ordinance of <hi>Preaching,</hi> becauſe he thinks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat this doth ſomewhat further him towards this happy and bleſſed End: But when ſuch a Duty is preſented before him, or ſuch a thing ſeems to be commanded and required of him in the ſame Word, which hath a ſhew, or perhaps a real conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent of worldly loſs, trouble, or inconvenience: This is ſuch a Stumbling-block in his way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that he cannot, or rather will not get over. So that here if he doth not the thing, he cries out, or ſecretly ejaculates with <hi>Naaman, The Lord par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don thy Servant in this thing, conſidering that he doth ſo much towards God beſides.</hi> Or when God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires and calls them forth to ſuch a particular Duty, they anſwer like thoſe invited to the Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding-Dinner, <hi>I pray thee, have me excuſed; for if I ſhould do ſo, I ſhould ſuffer damage in ſuch worldly matters.</hi> Nay, if he ſhould do the Duty, but yet <hi>he is offended that tribulation and perſecution is come upon him for it.</hi> This indeed is another ſtep fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but it comes ſhort of Heaven; for it makes to do the thing by halves, fearfully, and grudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, whereas God loves a willing Servant. But however, it is better ſo done, than not done at all. If we do a thing for God, we ſhould expect as much, and arm our ſelves before-hand, reſolving to be contented, and do the thing reſolutely and throughly for all, and not to be offended.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:105603:28"/>
            <p> I knew ſuch a Man (who herein did think and act more according to the Fleſh than according to the Spirit, we are ſure) who hath been very guilty and blame worthy in this nature. Of ſuch an one will I confeſs, yet of my ſelf I would not diſcover this mine own infirmity, but as a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Inſtruction to others, who ſhall perhaps read this, that from ſuch a poor &amp; mean Example, whom God hath carried through and preſerved all along (bleſſed be his <hi>Holy Name)</hi> he brought up alſo out of an horrible Pit, and out of the miry Clay (tho' the Deliverance be not yet thro' and perfect) for I hope that he will ſet my feet upon a Rock, and eſtabliſh my goings: <hi>And he hath put a new Song in my mouth, even praiſe unto our God: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhall ſee it, and fear, and ſhall truſt in the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 40. 2, 3. This is therefore written to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage others alſo to truſt in God, as they are ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him faithfully and truly in that Work he hath ſent them here on Earth for to do. <hi>Strengthen ye the weak hands, and confirm the feeble knees: Say to them that be of a fearful heart, Be ſtrong, fear not,</hi> Iſai. 35. 3, 4. <hi>And I will ſet up Shepherds over them, which ſhall feed them, and they ſhall fear no more nor be diſmayed, neither ſhall they be lacking, ſaith the Lord,</hi> Jer. 23. 4. That ſame Word by which all things and our ſelves were made, knows what is in Man, what he is liable, prone, and ſubject unto; and here he doth caution and provide againſt it.</p>
            <p>Fearfulneſs (both as to the confeſſion of the Truth as it is in Jeſus, or omiſſion of Duty to God)
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:105603:28"/> is a very great Sin, as may be conceived by that ſevere pain and puniſhment which is reſerved hereafter, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 8. for thoſe who are guilty of it. This (as may be underſtood from the forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Verſe) hinders and deprives from that precious Promiſe: <hi>He that overcometh, ſhall inherit all things; and I will be his God, and he ſhall be my Son.</hi> Which may be interpreted of overcoming that evil and corruption within our own Nature, or of the temptations which do beſet us from without; which many times we do not overcome, for fear of loſing ſo much pleaſure and ſweetneſs, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting our ſelves to pain and irkſomeneſs. But if the fear of this was rooted out of our Nature, we ſhould ſoon overcome thoſe temptations. Or it may be underſtood when we enter into warfare and fighting with the multitude of the Sinners and Tranſgreſſors: For every Miniſter upon his prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching or publiſhing of the Word of God faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>(And he that hath my Word, let him ſpeak my Word faithfully,</hi> Jer. 23. 28. doth hereby make an attack or onſet upon the Sinners of the World) who again are as ſo many <hi>Briars</hi> and <hi>Thorns</hi> which will prick and vex him; nay, it is a falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Scorpions, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 2. 6. who will claſp about, and endeavour to ſting him unto death.</p>
            <p>This was the Controverſie and War which the Prophets, Miniſters, and thoſe Worthies of old <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ime (all whom the Lord will recount) were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in. We read that ſome of them did ſucceed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the thing they did thus contend for, as to bring
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:105603:29"/> the high and mighty, and multitude of the People over to the Commandment and Will of God. Others again were perſecuted and killed as they did perſevere reſolutely in this their attempt and meſſage. Herein is God glorified, when his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant will ſuffer pain, inconvenience, hardſhip, or reſtraint to his body, loſs of outward livelihood, when he will not only hazard, but lay down his own life for the Word of his Miniſtry; and when he will bring things on to this upſhot and trial, God doth delight in the action of his Creatures. As he hath endued them with life and power of action, ſo theſe ſhould be put forth and uſed; for he hates the ſlothful Servant, who is negligent, idle, and doth nothing. Hardly any thing doth more provoke the eyes of his Glory, than diſtruſt and unbelief. Diſtruſt of his Faithfulneſs and Power, as if he would not, or could not carry them through. And then unbelief of his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Truth, that admit they ſhould loſe their All, even their own Life in his Service, as if he would not make it up unto them again in <hi>the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſinful Fear doth ariſe and proceed forth from Ignorance; for they imagine or apprehend there is more hurt and ſmart in the perſecution than really there is, and thereupon they decline it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not knowing throughly the nature of things, how there is nothing ſo bad but what may and can be endured. Every thing here is ſudden, tranſitory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and paſſeth away like a ſhadow: So that it may
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:105603:29"/> be born <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> yea, and it is to be choſen, if it doth tend unto Good in the latter end; ſuch is the very diſpoſal and eſtabliſhment of things. And the ſeveral Diſpenſations of God towards his Servants and People in this life, are that he might humble them, and prove them, <hi>to do them good at their lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end</hi> Deut. 8. 16. <hi>There hath no temptation taken you, but ſuch as is common to man: But God is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, who will not ſuffer you to be tempted above that you are able; but will alſo with the temptation make a way to eſcape, that ye may be able to bear it,</hi> 1 Cor. 10. 3. The Apoſtle doth not here ſo immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y mean theſe common Temptations which we meet with, to Pride, Luſt, and Senſuality, though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his is alſo true as to them: But he writes thus to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Church under a grievous and perſecuted ſtate, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd as it was under the fiery trial, enduring the worſt that Men could invent or inflict; which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rials were torment or death it ſelf. And yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt them God did by his Spirit ſupport and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear up the Hearts of his People; and many times <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he temptation or trial did kill the Body: So that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ere was no other eſcape or deliverance; but the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oul was by the falling of that Houſe (it remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g no longer fit for her Habitation) driven out, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd forced to take Wings like a Dove, and fly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay into the uppermoſt parts of the World, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e might get above, and remain in thoſe places <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Bleſſed, which are freed from all diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nce and hurt of evil Spirits, where God ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ipe away all tears from their eyes, <hi>and there ſhall</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:105603:30"/> 
               <hi>be no more death, nor ſorrow, nor crying, neither ſhall there be any more pain; for the former, things are paſſed away,</hi> Rev. 21. 4.</p>
            <p>Another reaſon why many People are ſo very afraid to endure trouble for the ſake of God, is, in that if they ſhould be caſt into Priſon, they would be hindred from his Publick Worſhip, or from doing the Work which God hath ſent them on this Earth for to do. Herein again they may be quieted and ſatisfied, that if they ſhould ſuffer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Will of God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 11. He doth not require Impoſſibilities, but accepts the Will for the Deed, when he ſees it is a real Intention which would come forth into Act accordingly, if there was power and opportunity. He may make it up in the Day of Recompence for the ſame Good, as they would have done if they ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been in full liberty and power of action. As Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is glorified in the Action, ſo likewiſe he is glor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fied in the manifold variety of the Condition o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Creatures. <hi>And all the Churches ſhall know th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I am he which ſearcheth the Reins and Hearts; and will give unto every one of you according to his Wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rev.</hi> 2. 23. Beſides what doth appear fort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> through them in the uppermoſt ſight, he dot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſearch (for ſo his Word imports) to know wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is yet further hid or wrapt up, or infolden in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to render unto every one according to what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Work was, or would be.</p>
            <p>Now let all the Churches (that is, according the ſignification at this Day, the People of the ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:105603:30"/> Opinions and Ways of Worſhip) be examined and ask'd, What have their Works been through their paſt Life? What have they done for God? The beſt and utmoſt anſwer that they can give, is, That they have conſtantly attended and frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his <hi>Ordinances</hi> of Worſhip from their youth up. They have heard, read, and ſpoken of many good <hi>words</hi> and precious <hi>truths.</hi> They have given Alms according to their ability, and they have ſpent much time in Prayer unto God; they have ſhewn forth Bowels of <hi>Compaſſion,</hi> and done what <hi>kindneſs</hi> they could for their <hi>Neighbour</hi> at all times. Such an account of their <hi>Stewardſhip</hi> as this they may give in. But have they managed and traded with all the Talents which the Lord of Heaven and Earth had committed unto them? Have they ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved God at all times with all their Power, and with all their Strength, and with all their Mind, and with all their Soul? Have they not omitted ſecret Duty at many and ſundry times? I do not mean that which is open and manifeſt in the ſight of the World, but what is known between God and their own Conſciences? Have they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the Commandment of the Lord, and executed his Judgments? Which Words <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form</hi> and <hi>Execute,</hi> as it is in the Scripture-mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 13. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. 17. doth import to do the thing throughly, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7. 5. and according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the utmoſt as is required. How many ſecret <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>otions of God's Spirit in them have they quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, deſpiſed, and diſobeyed? How many car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Reaſonings, Excuſes, and Fears have kept
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:105603:31"/> them off from ſuch and ſuch things which they ought to have done? How many things have been done out of reſpect, compliance, flattery, and pleaſing had to Man, which were not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with the pleaſing and approving of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unto God only? Even in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, how often have the Commandments and Traditions of Men been more carefully and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly obſerved, than the immediate Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God Himſelf? How often hath more Heed and Obedience been given unto ſuch Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Rules of Man's Deviſing and Wiſdom, or to the meer Saying of ſuch and ſuch Preachers, than to what the Holy Ghoſt enjoineth, or the Spirit it ſelf teacheth?</p>
            <p>I do not lay theſe things open to judge and upbraid my fellow Chriſtians; but that both they and my ſelf may ſee our Errors, Failings, and Neglects, in order to amend and avoid ſuch for the time to come: Neither do I this by way of accuſing my Brethren, to inform or make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion againſt them before God, to leſſen his preſent Favour and future Recompence; in that there is ſo little good and ſo much ill deſerving in their beſt godly Performances: <hi>For thou O Lord, knoweſt and underſtandeſt theſe things long before, and much more. O Lord, thou knoweſt al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> things, thou knoweſt that I love thee,</hi> John 21. 17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And ſo it is contrariwiſe; Lord, thou knoweſt all things; thou knoweſt that ſuch and ſuch Peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple do offend, diſpleaſe, and provoke thee. What<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:105603:31"/> are the ſurmiſes of the Ignorant, or the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations of the wicked and ungodly Multitude, God knows the ſinfulneſs of Sin, with the utmoſt malignity and evil deſerving thereof, more than the moſt invidious and rigid Perſon (as they call him) can lay it open, and declare it. A thought doth ariſe in ſome Hearts, as if by writing Words of Truth God was hereby put in mind, or the thing was hereby made worſe before him than really it is; and from hence doth ſpring up ſome part of that Root of Bitterneſs and Enmity againſt the Truth, whereby many are defiled. But here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they do err, not knowing the way of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, how it comes and is conveyed into Man; for as a Conduit Pipe is dry, and hath no Water in it ſelf, but what it receives or comes from the Fountain or River; ſo we are meer Creatures, and have nothing but what we have received: As Chriſt ſaid (in whom are hid all the meaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledge) <hi>A Man can receive nothing, except it be given him from above;</hi> ſo it is certain that we know nothing at all but what God knows long before; and he doth ſend and infuſe it in a ſecret and inviſible (but yet both ſenſible and intelligible) way into our Minds and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings. So we cannot put God in mind of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>any thing; but he doth put us in mind: Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly it is one Office of the Spirit to bring things to our remembrance.</p>
            <p>As for making things worſe than they are, this ſeems to be ſome what like unto him who accuſes
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:105603:32"/> our Brethren before God day and night: But here it is to be underſtood, that Satan and the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len apoſtate Spirits are Creatures of God, and were made by him. Tho' it ſeems hard to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, and much more difficult to utter concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt riſe and origin of Evil, yet this may be ſafely and truly affirmed, That what Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Underſtanding the miſerable Spirits have, they had it at firſt by Creation from God, notwithſtanding they have ſince ſpoiled, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, perverted, and turn'd it into Malice, Envy, and all manner of Evil: They are evil wholly, continually, and throughout; whereas Man is made up of a mixture of Good and Evil; with ſome the Good is predominant and weighing down; with others the Evil is ſo. So that it is to be thought and ſuppoſed, that God doth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold all mean Communications and Influences of Goodneſs, and of his Spirit, towards evil Spirits; which yet he doth day by day afford to the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Men, and that more or leſs, according as they deſerve and improve it, or neglect and abuſe it. So that let Satan do his worſt, as it is prover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bially and truly ſaid, <hi>God is above the Devil;</hi> ſo his Knowledge doth as much exceed the other's (who is a Creature, and by him made) as the whole Ocean doth a ſingle Drop of Water. In the 1ſt. and 2d. Chapter of <hi>Job,</hi> in the 3d. of <hi>Zechariah</hi> and in <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 10. we ſee and underſtand God's ſuperlative and over-ruling Goodneſs and Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, how he doth moderate the matter, and affirm
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:105603:32"/> it by the way of Favour and Mercy on the ſide of Mankind. And this is but as talking a little before the Day of Aſſize; an Emblem and Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner, how he will determine it eternally on their ſide at the laſt and great Day of Judgment, notwithſtanding all the Informations, Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Aggravations of Satan. And now if there ſhould be any of his Miniſters transformed into Miniſters of Righteouſneſs alike unto Satan in this, who draw up more heavy and falſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictments, than the true and very nature of the thing doth require and will bear: Or if the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience it ſelf (which is yet more) preſſed with Sin and Guilt, ſhould fore-caſt too grievous things, all this will not do one jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of harm in the Day of the Lord; for he who hath prepared his Throne for Judgment, knows all things in the World: <hi>He ſhall judge the World in righteouſneſs; he ſhall miniſter Judgment to the People in uprightneſs,</hi> Pſal. 9. 8. In the new Tranſlation it is ſaid, <hi>He ſhall miniſter true Judgment to the People. Who weighs the mountains in ſcales, and the hills in a balance,</hi> He will make things to hang even, exact, and equal. <hi>Judgment will I lay to the Line, and Righteouſneſs to the Plummet,</hi> Iſai. 28. 17. <hi>He ſhall judge the World with Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the People with his Truth,</hi> Pſal. 96. 13. <hi>With Righteouſneſs ſhall he judge the World, and the People with equity,</hi> Pſal. 98. 9. Now Equity is a mild thing, which doth ſtate, moderate, and adjuſt a matter: And then after all God doth reſerve Mercy, even after Judgment and Condemnation, for that is its proper place.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:105603:33"/>
            <p> At the laſt Day Mercy ſhall rejoice againſt Judgment in ſuch a ſignal, eminent, great, and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal a manner, even as to ſwallow up all Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Victory: <hi>When I am pacified toward thee for all that thou haſt done, ſaith the Lord God,</hi> Ezek. 16. 63. When this Song ſhall be ſung, <hi>Thou haſt taken away all thy Wrath; thou haſt turn'd thy ſelf from the fierceneſs of thine Anger,</hi> Pſal. 85. 3. God is more merciful than ever it entred into the Heart to conceive, or the Ear hath heard; that as it is written at the firſt Creation, <hi>The Morning-Stars ſang together, and all the Sons of God ſhouted for joy,</hi> Job. 38. 7. Now compare this with <hi>Iſai.</hi> 14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2. Lucifer is there called Son of the Morning; ſo that if ever he ſang for joy, it was before he fell from Heaven. And it is both poſſible and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that for joy, when he was firſt brought forth into being, he might ſing a Song of Praiſe and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment unto the great Creator of all Things. And ſo if we look back to <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 2, 4. There we find the wicked and ungodly of the World ſtyled <hi>The Sons of God;</hi> for ſo they are by Creation and Workmanſhip. This was freſh, and ſoon after the Creation; for we never, as I know of, find them ſo called again throughout all Scripture. So that by what may be gathered from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104. 30, 31. <hi>Thou reneweſt the face of the Earth: The Lord ſhall rejoice in his Works;</hi> So at the very laſt upſhot and end of all things, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Equity, and Mercy will diſplay and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that; that if ſo be the Morning Stars may not again ſing together, and all the Sons of God
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:105603:33"/> (obſerve that Particle <hi>all,</hi> including both the Sons by Creation, as well as thoſe by Grace and Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption) may not ſhout together for joy, yet at leaſt it may be ſomewhat more tolerable, than that certain, fearful looking for of Judgment, and the fiery Indignation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 27. or when they did believe and tremble, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. 19. They muſt indeed undergo the devouring Fire (for all Scripture muſt be fulfilled) and they muſt ſee and ſuffer al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; which in probability will be throughout a much longer duration than the time was, in which the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Inſtitutions did laſt, which were ſaid to be a Statute for ever; or as it is written, That <hi>the Ordinances of Day and Night ſhall not ceaſe while the Earth remaineth,</hi> Gen. 8. 23. Which <hi>Earth</hi> in the Book of Pſalms, is ſaid <hi>to be eſtabliſhed for ever, Pſal.</hi> 78. 69. Again it is written, <hi>If thoſe Ordinances depart from before me, ſaith the Lord, then the ſeed of</hi> Iſrael <hi>alſo ſhall ceaſe from being a Nation before me for ever,</hi> Jer. 31. 36. And yet the Seed of <hi>Iſrael</hi> doth at this day ſeem to ceaſe to be a Nation; as it is yet more certain, that this Earth at laſt ſhall paſs away, and the Ordinances of Day and Night ſhall then alſo ceaſe, and come to an utter end. But God only knows what may ſucceed after all this, when thoſe miſerable Creatures have lain under condemnation and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment a much longer ſpace of duration than ſix or ſeven thouſand Years now (within which time all this lower Creation, and the Works there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in probability will be determined and finiſhed) God will look down from the height of his San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:105603:34"/> (when the Pſalmiſt ſpoke thus by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, it was then to come) <hi>from Heaven will the Lord behold the Earth</hi> (yea, and who knows whether he will behold yet lower; <hi>If I make my Bed in Hell, behold thou art there) To hear the groaning of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, to looſe thoſe that are appointed to death,</hi> Pſal. 102. 19, 20. In the Margin there, it is <hi>Children of Death.</hi> This one portion of Scripture is of more worth than ten thouſand Worlds. If any thing of good or mitigation is intended to them, it will come in upon this account, That they are the Creatures of God, and his Workmanſhip. <hi>The Lord ſhall rejoice in his Works, and they ſhall recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, rejoice in the Lord their God.</hi> If thoſe very Creatures (who ſeem rejected <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 17. and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 13. by him) can but then call upon him by the Name of the Lord, and lay hold on him as <hi>Eſau</hi> did with his Father <hi>Iſaac</hi> (compare <hi>Gen.</hi> 27. 34, 38. with <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 16, 17.) <hi>And when</hi> Eſau <hi>heard the Words of his Father, he cried with a great and exceeding bitter cry, and ſaid unto his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Bleſs me, even me, O my Father.</hi> Here he continues and keeps up, and puts in mind of the Relation. After his Excuſe and Anſwer had, ſtill he doth continue and repeat, and again double the Words of his Relation: <hi>Haſt thou but one Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing? Bleſs me, even me alſo, O my Father; and</hi> Eſau <hi>lift up his voice, and wept.</hi> So it may be concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of thoſe condemned, forlorn, and miſerable Creatures, that after they have been long in wailing and gnaſhing of Teeth, with howling and great crying, if they can but then call upon
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:105603:34"/> Him by the Name of Creator, and remember, and lay it before him, <hi>That they are the work of his hands: Thy Mercy, O Lord, endureth for ever</hi> (it reaches and extends beyond the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, even throughout all Eternity) <hi>Forſake not the work of thine own hands,</hi> Pſal. 138. 8. Do not leave them for ever in utter deſpair and miſery. God hath more than one Bleſſing to Angels and Saints; he may make Devils and condemned Sinners Hewers of Stone and Drawers of Water, <hi>John</hi> 9. 2. That is, ſomewhat eaſe, and exempt them from the worſt pain and thraldom: For <hi>there is no difference between the</hi> Jew <hi>and the Greek:</hi> For there is no difference between the Fleſh of a Saint, and the Fleſh of a Sinner (and I ſuppoſe there is not much more as to the outward origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal frame and compoſure of Spirits of the ſame kind) <hi>For the ſame Lord over all</hi> (that is, Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) <hi>is rich unto all that call upon him: For whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall call upon the Name of the Lord, ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> Rom. 10. 12, 13. This is cited from <hi>Joel</hi> 2. 32. and there it is delivered: So that by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſiveneſs of the Word <hi>Whoſoever</hi> (which takes in all without exception) and from the Apoſtle's arguing, That <hi>the Lord is rich unto all that call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him:</hi> That is, he hath Goodneſs abundant and to ſpare (for he doth ten thouſand times exceed even that of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> or of the beſt and moſt tender Father; for 'tis he who created the Bowels, and put Compaſſion in them.) By the Riches of his Goodneſs he is obliged to do ſomewhat for every one that calls upon him. So that if theſe Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:105603:35"/> can, and do but call upon the Name of the Lord, though it will not be after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and nothing to an equal degree of that Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation the elect Servants of God are poſſeſſed of; yet they will at length be ſomewhat ſaved and delivered from that depth and grievouſneſs of pain and miſery which they have long groaned under. <hi>For I will not contend for ever, neither will I be always wroth; for the Spirit ſhould fail before me, and the Souls that I have made,</hi> Iſai. 57. 16. <hi>For God hath concluded them all in unbelief, that he might have mercy upon all,</hi> Rom. 11. 32. As the Wiſdom of God is manifold, ſo the Truths ariſing out of his Word, are of more univerſal latitude, and of lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger extent, even throughout the ſucceeding Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, than that particular occaſion upon which they were at firſt cited. For theſe two great Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures have a further meaning and ſignification, than to troubled and afflicted Conſciences, or to the temporal caſting off of the <hi>Jews.</hi> The ſame may be yet further underſtood from the very Nature of God (who is infinitely, eternally, and eſſentially good) and from the Analogy and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of things, that he will not contend for ever in the puniſhment and miſery of his Creatures; but he hath ſhut them all under deſerved, and the greater part under actual condemnation, that he might have mercy upon all. <hi>O the depth of the Riches both of the Wiſdom and Knowledge of God How unſearchable are his Judgments, and his Ways paſt finding out!</hi> was the Concluſion which the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:105603:35"/> Apoſtle made, when himſelf had before, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the meaſure of the Knowledge given him, ſearched and found out ſome of them. But thus he pronounceth concerning what yet remained behind, and which himſelf underſtood not any further.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If thou, Lord, ſhouldſt mark Iniquities, O Lord, who ſhall ſtand?</hi> Pſal. 130. 3. And <hi>Enter not into Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with thy Servant, for in thy ſight ſhall no man living be juſtified,</hi> Pſal. 143. 2. <hi>For all have ſinned and come ſhort of the Glory of God,</hi> Rom. 3. 23. The beſt Servant of God that was ever, or is now up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Earth, doth come ſhort of that Holineſs (as He is holy) and of performing that Duty in all things, and at all times, which God did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand or require of him. Such Truths are to be made known, which ſhew how theſe are ſo, let whatever imputation will be faſtned upon it. To come with Ropes about our Necks, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge our ſelves worthy of Death eternal; to donfeſs our Sin in the moſt aggravating Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; to arraign our ſelves, and make no other Plea than acknowledgment of our own Guilt; that we have tranſgreſſed againſt the Lord, and to cry our mightily and earneſtly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him for pardon and mercy: All this is the beſt and ſooneſt way to make our peace with God. So did <hi>David</hi> and the <hi>Prophets.</hi> Saith one, <hi>We lie down in our ſhame, and our confuſion covereth us; for we have ſinned againſt the Lord our God, from our youth even unto this day, and have not obeyed the</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:105603:36"/> 
               <hi>voice of the Lord our God.</hi> Jer. 3. 15. <hi>But we are all as an unclean thing, and all our Righteouſneſs are as filthy Rags,</hi> Iſai. 64. 6. Some may be apt to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, What need the Prophet mention this, for peradventure God might accept this Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as it is; whereas by vilifying and depretia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it as he doth, he may put God in mind, or move him not to accept it. What an abſurd and wrong imagination is here! For it was the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God which did firſt acquaint and make this known unto <hi>Iſaiah;</hi> and he ſpeaks it forth unto the People, in order to humble them, and make them have a low Conceit of their beſt Performances; To be as nothing in our own ſight; to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our own Guilt and Unworthineſs; to bear iniquity, and loath our ſelves for our Sins: This is the way to get the Favour and Mercy of God; for ſo did the holy Men and Women of old, who ſerved him, and were accepted by him.</p>
            <p>And ſo when God would tell People of their Sins and Tranſgreſſions, when they have done amiſs, and erred from his Commandments, he doth not now ſpeak unto the Inhabitants of the Earth out of the cloudy Pillar, or from the Battle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Heaven; but now he ſpeaks in the ſtill Voice of his Word and Spirit unto their Hearts and Conſciences: Which Word is yet more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and diſtinctly revealed unto ſome of his pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar and elect Servants; whom again he prompts by his Spirit, to ſpeak out, and publiſh the ſame Word unto others. And ſo they do not tell and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:105603:36"/> inform God, but God doth tell and inform them. Agreeable hereunto is that kind of ſpeaking unto <hi>Ezekiel, Go and ſhew the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael <hi>their Doings, and cauſe them to know the Abominations of their Fathers,</hi> Ezek. 20. 4. God ſees it, and is diſpleaſed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59. 15. He knows it, and is grieved: <hi>Forty years long was I grieved with this Generation,</hi> Pſal. 95. 10. His own Spirit is preſſed until it is actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſtirred up; which ſame Spirit he doth infuſe it into ſome Pipe here on Earth, either Man or Woman, who again doth receive, convey, and vent it forth, by publiſhing and making it known unto other Men and Women: <hi>I am preſſed under you, as a cart is preſſed with ſheaves.</hi> He doth here ſpeak after the manner of Men for our Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: And hereby we may apprehend how the intercourſe is between God and his Creatures, that whatever good is done here on Earth, it is (if I may expreſs it) the Actings of God through his Creatures. Hence are thoſe Sayings in Scripture, <hi>I will dwell in them, and walk in them,</hi> 2 Cor. 10. 6. <hi>God dwelleth in you,</hi> 2 Cor. 10. 16. <hi>It is not you that ſpeak, but the Spirit of your Father which ſpeaketh in you,</hi> Mat. 10. 20. <hi>God is in you of a truth,</hi> 2 Cor. 14. 25. And where it is ſo, he is a continued Principle of right action and well-doing.</p>
            <p>Hereby we may perceive the ſuperlative and infinite and exceeding Goodneſs of God, who is the Root and Foundation of all Beings. He doth as much exceed all the Inhabitants of the Earth (take them all in their Generations and Places,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:105603:37"/> when and where they were on this Earth) as the whole Earth doth exceed an handful of Duſt or Sand. We ſee how much one good Man doth, how he reaches forth and extends his Goodneſs far and near, and he is always ſeeking Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities for exerting of it. If he is a Man of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Wiſdom, the Lips of the Wiſe diſperſe Knowledge, and it is unexpreſſible how much good his Words may do, when the ſound thereof goes out far and near; and yet much more good will they do, when <hi>they are written for the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations to come,</hi> Pſal. 102. 18. and for after-Ages. I have often thought, when I ſee a juſt Man, who is <hi>perfect in his Generations, and walketh with God,</hi> Gen. 6. 9. who is right towards God in all things, and withal zealous, diligent, and active in his Service (as God hath all along in the forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Generations, and in the ſeveral Countries raiſed up ſuch ſingle Inſtruments) what a bleſſed World would there be, if hundreds and thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands did the like! Each Man would bring over his thouſand, and ten would put ten thouſand to flight, to the utter and thorough ſubduing of the whole World of the Sinners and Ungodly: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they appearing ſingular in their Generations, it comes to paſs through the great and continued oppoſition of Satan (the name of whoſe Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is Legion, for they are many) that ſuch could not effect any great matter; or if they did ſomewhat (for what is of God will ſtand in ſpight of Men o Devils) yet it was not in that degree to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:105603:37"/> which they did aim and intend it. They were like light ſhining in a dark place, which others at a diſtance could juſt ſee the glimpſe and appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of, but they had no benefit thereof. And then this burning light in his Generation was ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther blown out (for the Devil hath ſometimes power to kill the Witneſſes) or waſted ſooner; or if none of theſe did happen, it muſt at length be naturally ſpent out. In this alſo they were like the Captain of their Salvation: <hi>I have trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the Wine-preſs alone, and of the People there was none with me,</hi> Iſa. 63. 3. For when once they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to be bruiſed, or the ſparkles of Blood do fly, then the People will be ſure to keep far enough off. Now God did act all along in thoſe ſingle Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; but why he did not ſtir up more, or others alſo; or if he did preſs upon them with the ſecret motions of his Spirit, which they did not obey: Whereas he could have been upon them, even up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them with a ſtrong hand alſo, and with ſuch an over-ruling preſſure of their Spirits, that they ſhould have been likewiſe actually ſtirred up: But it was not ſo, the reaſons hereof how it was then for the great Ends of his own Glory and Man's Trial, himſelf will rehearſe when he writeth up the People.</p>
            <p>But this is certain, that in thoſe Times of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Reformation, which are now drawing on in theſe latter Days, he will raiſe up a proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able number of Inſtruments, even thouſands and ten thouſands, who ſhall certainly and actually
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:105603:38"/> effect the very thing; <hi>Until the Spirit be poured down upon us from on high,</hi> Iſai. 32. 15. The word <hi>Pour,</hi> doth denote in a much more large and Plentiful manner, than that dropping and diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Spirit heretofore, only in ſuch peculiar and choſen Veſſels. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs in the laſt days,</hi> ſaith God, I <hi>will pour out of my Spirit upon all fleſh,</hi> Acts 1. 17. Thus it will be in the very laſt Days at the concluſion and ſhutting up of all. But if we look back unto the foregoing Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as to the ſtate and progreſs of pure and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled Religion, or as to the Knowledge of God in this or other Countries, that of <hi>Jeremiah</hi> is here true and applicable, <hi>They have gone backward, and not forward: Since the day that your Fathers came forth of the Land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>unto this day, I have even ſent unto you all my Servants the Prophets, daily riſing up early, and ſending them; yet they hearkned not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, nor enclined their ear; but hardned their neck, they did worſe than their Fathers,</hi> Jer. 7. 25, 26. When God did make an appearance and ſhew himſelf by Miracles and Signs, then People were for the time in ſome meaſure as they ſhould be. But when they were over, and the remembrance of them did go off and vaniſh by degrees, then they did return to their former Sin, Corruption, Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, cuſtomary and formal Worſhip. So it hath been ſince the days of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, when we were redeem'd from ſpiritual <hi>Egypt,</hi> from the Bondage and Hurt of Sin, Satan, and Death, then indeed there was a peculiar People; but
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:105603:38"/> ever ſince they have <hi>gone backward and not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi> And ſo when the People of this Nation, about an hundred and fifty Years ſince, came out of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Darkneſs of Popiſh Ignorance and from out of the Wilderneſs of Superſtition, into a fuller and clearer light of the Goſpel, which they worked through, and brought out from the very fire; then indeed were the Churches cleanſed and bright: But almoſt ever ſince it may be ſaid, They have <hi>gone backward, and not forward.</hi> When the Storm of Perſecution is over them, then it doth rouze up their Zeal, their greater Fear of God, and their greater Concern for the Truth and Spirituality of his Worſhip. This Fan doth alſo purge the Floor as to blow away the Chaff of Hypocrites, and gather the Wheat of real, firm, ſincere Chriſtians more cloſe together. But when that is over, the others come in again, and they are mingled together, and they do lie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly one with another.</p>
            <p>At this day the Churches have reſt and free liberty of Worſhip, according to their ſeveral Opinions and Perſuaſions; yet they have <hi>gone backward, and not forward.</hi> For is there not a <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicean</hi> lukewarmneſs, and indifferency ſpread throughout them all? Are not the Ordinances of Prayer and Preaching become cold, flat, dull, and low? Do they mount up as Eagles, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 40. 31. Or rather do they not ſtill <hi>lie among the Pots, Pſal.</hi> 68. 13. Inſtead of <hi>publiſhing the Name of the Lord, aſcribe ye Greatneſs unto our God,</hi> Deut. 32. 3.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:105603:39"/> and ſpeaking of the <hi>wonderful Works of God,</hi> Acts 2. 11. they are taken up with mans Notions, Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and Phraſes; and they are bewildered in the little things of this lower World; for they do not underſtand even them throughly and clearly. Where ſeems to be a little pure and primitive Chriſtianity, is not there much Ignorance and coming ſhort of the Knowledge of the Things of God, as they ought to be known? There are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome affected Phraſes of their own, which they harp and inſiſt altogether on; or there is a preference of ſome ſelect parts and portions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, before the whole Word of God; all which ought to be brought in equally upon occaſion, without preferring one thing before another, or at leaſt not to make the one a pretence to ſhut out the other. Are there not dark Speeches uſed (if it be not ſometimes unintelligible and myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal nonſence) whereas the time now is that they ſhould ſpeak no more to us in Proverbs, but they ſhould ſhew us plainly of the <hi>Father,</hi> John 16. 25. And in theſe larer times <hi>the Spirit ſpeaketh expreſly,</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 1. yea, and clearly, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch things as may be underſtood; not in Words which Man's Wiſdom teacheth (not in humane affected Phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) but which the Holy Ghoſt teacheth, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſpiritual with ſpiritual.</p>
            <p>And compare Scripture with Scripture, we ſhall find that ſuch, whether they be Men or Wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men, who ſay when the Lord hath not ſpoken, or who ſpeak <hi>a Viſion of their own heart, and not out</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:105603:39"/> 
               <hi>of the mouth of the Lord,</hi> Jer. 23. 16. <hi>Which prophecy out of their own heart,</hi> Ezek. 13. 17. Or who ſay that <hi>it ſhall ſo come to paſs,</hi> when the Lord hath not commanded them, and it will not come to paſs, and the thing doth not follow, ſuch are preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous: <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. 22. They take God's Name in vain, and a Woe is now pronounced againſt them, which at laſt will fall down upon them to their own miſery and condemnation.</p>
            <p>Is it not in ſome meaſure fulfilled at this day? We ſee not our Signs, <hi>there is no more any Prophet, neither is there any among us that knoweth how long,</hi> Pſal. 74. 9. That knoweth any thing certainly from God (as in times paſt he did reveal his Secret un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Servants the Prophets) or how long this Judgment of the Sword will be upon the Nations, nor after what manner and when God will work Salvation, and eſtabliſh Peace in the midſt of the Earth: <hi>For God is my King of old, working Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the midſt of the Earth,</hi> Pſal. 74. 12. <hi>I will be thy King; Where is any other that may ſave thee in all thy Cities and thy Judges? of whom thou ſaidſt, Give me a King and Princes,</hi> Hoſ. 13. 12. Theſe things will ſo be, when God doth reign imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately over the Hearts of all Men; and they yield that Obedience unto him, as now they do to their Kings and Governours after the Fleſh. But at this day it is fulfilled, <hi>Therefore night ſhall be upon you, that ye ſhall not divine; and the Sun ſhall go down over the Prophets, and it ſhall be dark over them; then ſhall the Seers be aſhamed, and the Diviners con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded;</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:105603:40"/> 
               <hi>yea, they ſhall all cover their Lips, for there is no anſwer of God,</hi> Mic. 3. 6, 7. Conſider through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of this, all ye Preachers in the ſeveral Churches and Congregations; and do ye not ſenſibly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Truth of this laſt? There is no anſwer of God. There is at this day (and accordingly he that is moſt ſpiritual, and knows moſt of God, doth moſt ſenſibly perceive it) the face of the Covering and the Veil that is ſpread over all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25. 7. There is a Veil and Covering over the Hearts and Underſtandings of Men (I feel it upon mine own) that they have not that conſtant lively Faith and clear Knowledge of the future and inviſible things of God, as was in the days of <hi>Moſes,</hi> or of Chriſt, or as themſelves had in former times when they were illuminated, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 32. Or as themſelves ſhall have, when God ſhall be pleaſed, according to his gracious Promiſe here, to deſtroy that Covering and Veil, and to break it that we may ſee through. <hi>But even unto this day, when</hi> Moſes <hi>is read, the Vail is upon their Hearts; nevertheleſs when it ſhall turn to the Lord, the Veil ſhall be taken away,</hi> 2 Cor. 3. 15, 16.</p>
            <p>Religion is now at a low ebb, I do not mean as to outward Worſhip, the Profeſſion, Appearance, and Shew thereof; for that was retained all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long throughout the foregoing Generations: But ſo it is as to the walking in all the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord blameleſs, in all Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs. To ſhew the exceeding ſtreſs that the People lay upon this thing of their going
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:105603:40"/> conſtantly to the place, and their performing the outward act of Worſhip, the Holy Ghoſt doth repeat it three times in his Caution concerning it: <hi>Truſt ye not in lying Words, ſaying, The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord are theſe, Jer.</hi> 7. 4. That is as much as to ſay, it is a lying and falſe Word, let People repeat it over and over, and inſiſt upon it never ſo much. It is not the bare going to Church, or to ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, is all that God doth require of Men and Women; nor is this ſufficient to bring them to Heaven. To ſay or affirm that this is all which God doth require, or that this with no more ado will bring them to Heaven, is a lying Word: For the Lord hath ſhewed in the foregoing Verſe, what he doth require of Men; namely, Amend your ways and your doings, and I will cauſe you to dwell in this place. This is the way to be fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and for ever to abide in the high and bleſſed place of Heaven. Again he finds fault, <hi>Will ye ſteal, murder, and commit adultery, and ſwear falſly, and burn incenſe to</hi> Baal, <hi>and walk after other Gods whom ye know not</hi> (here the Prophet enumerates the breach of Six Commandments, and in like manner it may be applied to the other Four, <hi>viz.</hi> Sabbath-breaking, Diſhonouring of Parents, Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and Covetouſneſs) <hi>and come and ſtand before me in this Houſe which is called by my Name, and ſay, We are delivered to do all theſe Abominations? Is this Houſe which is called by my Name, become a Den of Robbers in your eyes? behold, even I have ſeen it,</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:105603:41"/> 
               <hi>ſaith the Lord,</hi> Jer. 7. 9, 10, 11. So that the Inference is natural and neceſſary, That it is not the going to Church, or to any other Place of his Worſhip upon the Lord's Day, or upon every Week-Day, will ſerve to make an atonement, or blind and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive God for the breach and tranſgreſſions of his Laws and Commandments; for he doth here ſay, <hi>I have ſeen it,</hi> even through this Veil of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie; let them think or ſay what they will, that their Trade, or Buſineſs, or Neceſſity of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs do require them ſo to do. To the ſame purpoſe is the firſt Chapter of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> throughout: <hi>I hate, I deſpiſe your Feaſt-days, and I will not ſmell in your ſolemn Aſſemblies. Tho' ye offer your Burnt-offerings and Meat-offerings, I will not accept them, neither will I regard the Peace-offering of your Fat Beaſts. Take thou away from me the noiſe of thy Songs, for I will not hear the melody of thy Viols</hi> (what muſt we do then!) <hi>But let Judgment run down as Waters, and Righteouſneſs as a mighty Stream. Have ye offered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me Sacrifices and Offerings in the Wilderneſs forty Years, O Houſe of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Amos</hi> 5. 21, 22, 23, 24, 25. Have ye worſhipped me according to your ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Ways and Congregations in this Wilderneſs of the Earth (where one is at a loſs to find the right Way through your manifold Opinions and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions) for almoſt ſix thouſand Years, O ye Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Men? But ſtill ye have continued in your own Doings, and in the things ye have made to your ſelves, whereas that <hi>is the true Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle which the Lord pitched, and not Man,</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:105603:41"/> Heb. 8. 2. And now what if God himſelf ſhould ſay in the laſt Day, as he doth now ſpeak from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in this his Word. <hi>I hate, I deſpiſe, I will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, neither will I regard your Burnt offerings, Meat-offerings, and Peace-offerings?</hi> Which he himſelf did yet command and inſtitute, and Man did then uſe them to pleaſe, atone, and be reconciled to Almighty God.</p>
            <p>This is to be underſtood by the way, that God will one day ſpeak himſelf in perſon, with a loud and outward audible Voice, what he doth now ſpeak from Heaven in the ſtill Voice of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, or in the Scriptures (which are his Epiſtle ſent unto the Inhabitants of the Earth.) And whereas with many Men their Letters are power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but their bodily Preſence is weak and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, it will be contrariwiſe as to God: For his Word now (as written or ſpoken by Men) is weakneſs, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 25. But when himſelf ſhall utter his Voice, <hi>the Earth will melt,</hi> Pſal. 46. 6. <hi>The Heavens ſhall paſs away with a great noiſe, and the Elements ſhall melt with fervent heat,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 10. <hi>For the Lord himſelf ſhall deſcend with a ſhout, with the Voice of the Archangel, and with the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet of God,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4. 16. So that he will make a yet greater impreſſion, and cauſe a greater ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, not only upon the living Creatures, but alſo upon the very material Works of God, even all the World over; than that manner of giving the Law did formerly upon the ſingle and particular place of Mount <hi>Sinai;</hi> concerning which, ſee <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 17, 18. 19.</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:105603:42"/>
            <p> So it will be pronounced concerning the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Acts and Parts of Worſhip, outward Prayer, Praiſe, Hearing the Word, Baptiſm, and the Lord's Supper. Not that theſe are to be caſt off and neglected; in no wiſe: But yet ſo it is when it doth become the Sacrifice of Fools, the Sacrifice of Sinners and Tranſgreſſors; for they provoke God, and deceive themſelves (whereby they are Fools) when they keep up one with another; that is, when they worſhip God, and yet continue in ſin and tranſgreſſion. The whole Scripture is full to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            <p>But here it may be ſurmiſed, That if the caſe is ſo, it is good for ſuch not to worſhip God at all. But all Men cannot receive this Saying, but unto whom it is given; for Worſhip is due from every Creature unto God; and theſe things are written, not that they ſhould caſt off and neglect it: in no wiſe: But that every one ſhould turn away from his Iniquities, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 26. and ceaſe from all manner of ſin and tranſgreſſion. And then they are to obey all the Commandments of God, which relate to Good or Evil, Righteouſneſs or Wrong, Truth or Falſhood, enjoying the one, and forbidding the other, as well as they do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready obey thoſe his Commandments, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to his Worſhip. Except they do this alſo, they cannot be ſaved, and all their Worſhip will ſignifie nothing. It is ſtrange, but yet true and common, That many People of both Sexes ſhould go on blindly and ignorantly, for thirty,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:105603:42"/> forty, fifty, and ſixty Years, yea, throughout all their life, in this Deceit of being Worſhippers of God, and yet not doing his Will; whereas it is written ſo plainly, that every Capacity may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it. <hi>Now we know that God heareth not Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; but if any Man be a Worſhipper of God, and doth his Will, him he heareth,</hi> John 9. 31. As we read that Prayer of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe which God made unto his People by <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> of <hi>Levi</hi> he ſaid, <hi>Bleſs, Lord, his Subſtance, and accept the Work of his Hands,</hi> Deut. 33. 8, 11. <hi>Remember all thy Offerings, and accept thy Burnt-ſacrifice. Selah.</hi> Pſal. 20. 3. <hi>They ſhall come up with acceptance on mine Altars,</hi> Iſai. 60. 7. and <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20. 40, 41. We learn this Word of Inſtruction (which may make us to fear and take heed, and beg pardon for the Iniquity of our holy things, and to pray inſtantly and continually for acceptance) that in all things we do in order to God, or pertaining to Religion, as it is commonly named or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, unleſs God do accept thereof, it all ſignifies nothing: Nay, what is yet further, <hi>It is as cutting of a Dog's neck</hi> (there is not much in that) <hi>it is as offering Swines blood</hi> (this doth diſpleaſe God) <hi>it is as bleſſing an Idol,</hi> Iſai. 66. 3. which is the higheſt and ſuperlative degree of provoking God to the greateſt manner that poſſibly can be. So they do rather diſpleaſe than pleaſe; they make God to be further off, and more angry rather than bring him near, and make him reconciled unto us. Hear this Word, all ye People of <hi>England,</hi> that
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:105603:43"/> enter in at the Church-doors, or Meeting-Houſes, to praiſe the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Another thing wherein ye are</hi> defective and <hi>found wanting, is this, For they ſay and do not,</hi> Mat. 23. 2. They hear, read, and talk of many good Words and precious Truths, but they do not turn them into practice and ſuitable action. It is recorded of <hi>Moſes</hi> the Servant of the Lord, <hi>He was mighty in Words and in Deeds,</hi> Acts 7. 22. ſo he was for both; and therein he pleaſed and was accepted by God, who had hereupon a favour and love towards him: But this belongs not to the nominal, nor yet to the real Chriſtians of this Age, who make a fair ſhew in the Fleſh, and they are ſincere, and of the better ſort; yet herein they are found wanting, many of them are mighty in Words, but not in Deeds. They do talk of the higheſt Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Attainments of Religion, and they do conceive, ſpeak, read, hear, and write of the great Truths of God; but how to perform the ſame at all times, and in all places, and in reference to all Perſons, they find not. Towards the publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and making known theſe Truths throughout all this Region, or to hazard, or even to ſuffer actual tribulation for the Word's ſake, they are offended, and themſelves will not run the riſque and experience of it. The like Character is given unto him who is greater than <hi>Moſes,</hi> with a tranſverſal of the ſame Words, <hi>Jeſus of</hi> Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, <hi>a Prophet, mighty in deed and in word before God, and before all the People,</hi> Luke 24. 19. The
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:105603:43"/> Holy Ghoſt hereby ſignifying, that he did actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally more good than himſelf talked of; and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he did exceed <hi>Moſes</hi> and all the Children of God: For with them their Thoughts and Words do riſe higher than their Actions. For none ever did, nor yet can obey and do more for God, than he doth think or ſpeak of. But their Performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Doings come ſhort of their Words, as both Words and Actions do come ſhort of their Thoughts; for many, good, excellent, high, great, and glorious Things are thought of, which are never ſpoken out. But this is Man's fault and infirmity; for every thing that is good and true, ought to be ſpoken out; and if poſſible the ſame is to be put into practice. But where power is wanting, or opportunity is not to be had, there it ſhould come forth into will and real en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour; ſo that in good and duty we ſhould ſtill go as far as we can.</p>
            <p>If we ſeek out of the Book of the Lord, and read, we ſhall there find, that the whole of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind is diſtinguiſhed, not into ſuch Names as we give one another, of Papiſt, Proteſtant, Church-of-England-man, Presbyterian, Independent, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſt, Quaker, Sabbatarian, Socinian, Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or ſuch-like; but into Righteous and Wicked, <hi>they that ſerve God, and they that ſerve him not,</hi> Mal. 3. 18. This ſerving of God is not calling him their God, nor yet ſtyling themſelves the Children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> nor yet the ranking themſelves among the Members of a pure Church at this Day; nor
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:105603:44"/> yet paying unto God Acts of Worſhip every mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and evening; for whoſoever keeps all the parts and times of Worſhip, and yet will not obey one point of the Law of God, when he doth all the reſt, he is guilty of all, and an ungodly Man for all that. But this is the Service of God to do all his Will and Pleaſure; for as to our matters ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Fleſh, it is not the bare calling him Maſter, or living in his Family, or paying unto him outward Reſpect; all this will not make them to be Servants indeed: But it is the conſtant do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Buſineſs, according to what they are bid and commanded from time to time. The Spirit of God doth foreſee there is a ſort of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who goon in that Deceit of calling themſelves of the Holy City, and ſtaying upon the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> of worſhipping God, and ſpeaking honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably of his Name: Theſe would take it ill if any one ſhould ſay they did not ſerve God. As indeed they do not, tho' <hi>they ſerve with an Offering, and weary themſelves with Incenſe,</hi> Iſai. 43. 23. Tho' they ſpend never ſo much time in outward Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and take all the Opportunities and Seaſons for it; yet in the meaning and requiring of the Holy Ghoſt, they do not properly and truly ſerve God, unleſs they do confirm all the Words of his Law to do them. The ſame Spirit doth caution us hereof, and give us to underſtand as much by what is written, <hi>Ye Miniſters of his that do his pleaſure,</hi> Pſal. 103. 21. Hereby intimating that there are ſuch who think themſelves, and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:105603:44"/> are called by the World <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and <hi>Servants of God,</hi> who yet do not his Pleaſure: <hi>Why call ye me Lord, Lord, and do not the things which I ſay,</hi> Luke 6. 46. And yet more plainly this is ſignified by what the Spirit ſaith, <hi>His Servants ſhall ſerve him,</hi> Rev. 22. 3 This is brought in upon deſcribing the manner of the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> above, which herein is oppoſite and different from that on Earth; for many here are called Servants of God, who do not in deed and in truth ſerve him: Whereas ſuch only, who do in deed and in truth ſerve him, ſhall be admitted there. <hi>Not every one that ſaith unto me, Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven; but he that doth the Will of my Father which is in Heaven. Many will ſay to me in that day, Lord, Lord, have we not propheſied in thy Name, and in thy Name caſt out Devils? and in thy Name done many wonderful Works; and I will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs unto them, I never knew ye; depart from me, ye that work Iniquity,</hi> Mat. 7. 21, 22, 23.</p>
            <p>Theſe things I have written, not that I had ought as of my ſelf to accuſe my Nation of; but to manifeſt from the Word which flatters none, but declares unto all Men what his thoughts and ways are; that though a form of Godlineſs is ſpread and diffuſed throughout the ſeveral Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Places of this Iſland; yet they all come ſhort of the Power and ſubſtance thereof. And as we do all look for the appearance of the Great GOD, who ſhall render to every Man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:105603:45"/> to his Work, both ye and my ſelf are to be diligent, that we may be found of Him without ſpot and blameleſs. I ſpeak not theſe things as a Man; but they do proceed forth from the Word and Spirit of the Lord, and from Him that gives Man Knowledge; who ſees all this, and much more, and is diſpleaſed. As Wounds and Bruiſes, and putrifying Sores are launced in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to a cure; ſo theſe things are laid open before all the Churches (which they may at leaſt come to the ſight, hearing, or rumour of) that they may know ſuch things have been written, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Commandment of <hi>the God of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>they amend their Ways and their Doings,</hi> Jer. 7. 3. if they intend to have the Favour of God now, be accepted of Him at laſt, and if they would dwell with him in the higheſt Heavens for evermore. <hi>Amen, ſaith my Soul; come, Lord Jeſus, come quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:105603:45"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
